<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="ha221" >"221. Ibn Umar (Allah be pleased with both of them) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying in connection with Ramadan:\n"
        "Do not fast till you see the new moon, and do not break fast till you see it; but if the weather is cloudy calculate about it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha222" >"222. Anas (Allah be pleased with him) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "Take meal a little before dawn, for there is a blessing in taking meal at that time.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha223" > "223. 'Amr b. al-'As reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "The difference between our fasting and that of the people of the Book is eating shortly before dawn.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha224" >"224. Zaid b. Thabit (Allah be pleased with him) said:\n"
        "We took meal shortly before dawn along with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). We then stood up for prayer. I said: How much span of time was there between the two (acts, i. e. taking of Sahri and observing of prayer)? He said (a span of reciting) fifty verses.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha225" >"225. Sahl b. Sa'd (Allah be pleased with him) repotted Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "The people will continue to prosper as long as they hasten the breaking of the fast.(sahih  Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha226" >"226. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) said that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) kissed one of his wives while he was fasting, and then she ('A'isha) smiled (as she narrated).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha227" > "227. Abu Huraira reported that a person had intercourse with his wife during Ramadan (while fasting). He asked for the religious verdict (about it) from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), whereupon he (the Holy Prophet) said:\n"
        "Can you find a slave (to grant him freedom)? He said: No. He (the Prophet again) said: Can you afford to observe fasts for two (consecutive) months? He said: No. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Then feed sixty poor men.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha228" >"228. Ibn Abbas (Allah be pleased with him) reported:\n"
        "Do not condemn one who observes fast, or one who does not observe (in a journey). for the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) observed fast in a journey or he did not observe it (too).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha229" >"229. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported that the Quraish used to fast on the day of 'Ashura in the pre-Islamic days and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) also observed it. When he migrated to Medina, he himself observed this fast and commanded (others) to observe it. But when fasting during the month of Ramadan was made obligatory he said:\n"
        "He who wishes to observe this fast may do so, and he who wishes to abandon it may do so.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha230" > "230. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) said that the Prophet (ﷺ) forbade to observe fast on two days-the day of Fitr and the day of Adha.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha231" >"231. Abu Huraira (Allah be pleased with him) reported the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "None among you should observe fast on Friday, but only that he observes fast before it and after it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha232" >"232. Ibn Abbas (Allah be pleased with them) reported:\n"
        "A woman came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said: Messenger of Allah, my mother has died and there is due from her a fast of vow; should I fast on her behalf? Thereupon he said: You see that if your mother had died in debt, would it not have been paid on her behalf? She said: Yes. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Then observe fast on behalf of your mother.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha233" >"233. Abu Huraira (Allah be pleased with him) reported Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "If any one of you is invited to a meal when he is fasting, he should say:\" I am fasting.\"(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha234" > "234. Abu Huraira (Allah be pleased with him) reported:\n"
        "When any one of you gets up in the morning in the state of fasting, he should neither use obscene language nor do any act of ignorance. And if anyone slanders him or quarrels with him, he should say:\" I am fasting, I am fasting.\"(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha235" > "235. Abu Huraira and Abu Sa'id (Allah be pleased with both of them) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) (as saying):\n"
        "Allah, the Exalted and Majestic, said: Fast (is exclusively) meant for Me and I would give its reward. There are two (occasions) of joy for the observer of fast. He feels joy when he breaks the fast and he is happy when he meets Allah. By Allah in Whose Hand is the life of Muhammad, the breath of the observer of fast is sweeter to Allah than the fragrance of musk.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha236" >"236. Sahl b. Sa'd (Allah be pleased with him) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "In Paradise there is a gate which is called Rayyan through which only the people who fast would enter on the Day on Resurrection. None else would enter along with them. It would be proclaimed: Where are the people who fast that they should be admitted into it? And when the last of them would enter, it would be closed and no one would enter it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha237" >"237. Abu Sa'id al Khudri (Allah be pleased with him) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "Every servant of Allah who observes fast for a day in the way of Allah, Allah would remove, because of this day, his face farther from the Fire (of Hell) to the extent of seventy years' distance.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha238" > "238. Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "If anyone forgets that he is fasting and eats or drinks he should complete his fast, for it is only Allah Who has fed him and given him drink.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha239" >"239. 'A'isha, the Mother of the Believers (Allah be pleased with her), reported that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) used to fast (so continuously) that we said that he would not break, and did not fast at all till we said that he would not fast. And I did not see the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) completing the fast of a month, but that of Ramadan, and I did not see him fasting more in any other month than that of Sha'ban.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha240" >"240. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported:\n"
        "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) did not observe fast in any month of the year more than in the month of Sha'ban, and used to say: Do as many deeds as you are capable of doing, for Allah will not become weary (of giving you reward), but you would be tired (of doing good deeds) ; and he also said: The deed liked most by Allah is one to which the doer adheres constantly even if it is small.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha241" >"241. 'Abdullah b. 'Amr (Allah be pleased with them) reported:\n"
        "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to me: Recite the whole of the Qur'An during every month. I said: I find power (to recite it) in a shorter period. He said: Then recite it in twenty nights. I said: I find power (to recite it in a shorter period even than this), whereupon he said: Then recite it in seven (nights) and do not exceed beyond it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha242" >"242. 'Abdullah b. 'Amr b. al-'As (Allah be pleased with them) reported that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:\n"
        "'Abdullah, don't be like so and so who observed prayer during the whole night and then abandoned it (altogether).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha243" >"243. 'Abdullah b. 'Amr (Allah be pleased with both of them) reported:\n"
        "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to me: I have been informed that you stand for prayer the whole of night and fast during the day. I said: I do that, whereupon he said: If you did that you in fact strained heavily your eyes and made yourself weak. There is a right of your eyes (upon you) and a right of your self (upon you) and a right of your family (upon you). Stand for prayer and sleep. observe fasts and break (them).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha244" >"244. 'Abdullah b. 'Amr (Allah be pleased with both of them) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "With Allah the best fasting is that of David and the best prayer is that of David (peace be upon him) for he slept half of the night and stood for prayer for the third of it and (then) slept the sixth part of it and he observed fast one day and broke on the other.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha245" >"245. Abu Qatada Ansari (Allah be pleased with him) reported that Allah's Massenger (ﷺ) was asked about fasting on Monday, whereupon he said:\n"
        "It is (the day) when I was born and revelation was sent down to me.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha246" >"246. Abu Ayyub al-Ansari (Allah be pleased with him) reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "He who observed the fast of Ramadan and then followed it with six (fasts) of Shawwal. it would be as if he fasted perpetually.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha247" >"247. Salim reported on the authority of his father that a person saw Lailat-ul- Qadr on the 27th (of Ramadan). Thereupon Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) said:\n"
        "I see that your dreams agree regarding the last ten (nights of Ramadan). So seek it on an odd number (of these ten nights).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha248" >"248. Ibn 'Umar (Allah be pleased with both of them) reported that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) used to observe i'tikaf in the last ten days of Ramadan.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha249" >"249. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported that the Messenger of Allah (may peace he upon him) used to observe i'tikif in the last ten days of Ramadan till Allah called him back (to his heavenly home). Then his wives observed i'tikaf after him.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha250" >"250. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported that when the last ten nights began Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) kept awake at night (for prayer and devotion), wakened his family, and prepared himself to observe prayer (with more vigour).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha251" >"251. 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) used to exert himself in devotion during the last ten nights to a greater extent than at any other time.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha252" >"252. Mu'awiya b. Suwaid b. Muqarrin reporxed:\n"
        "I visited al-Bara' b. 'Azib and heard him say: Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) commanded us to do seven things and forbade us to do seven (things). He commanded us to visit the sick, to follow the funeral procession, to answer the sneezer, to fulfil the vow, to help the poor, to accept the invitation and to greet everybody, and he forbade us to wear rings or gold rings, to drink in silver (vessels), and to use the saddle cloth made of red silk, and to wear garments made of Qassi material, or garments made of silk or brocade and velvet.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha253" >"253. Abd al-Rahman reported on the authority of his mother's sister Umm Salama who said that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said:\n"
        "He who drank in vessels of gold or silver he in fact drank down in his belly the fire of Hell.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha254" >"254. 'Ali reported that Ukaidir of Duma presented to Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) a silk garment, and he presented it to 'Ali. and said:\n"
        "Tear it to make head covering for Fitimas out of it. This tradition is transmitted on the authority of Abu Bakr, and Abu Kuraib said: Among the women.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha255" >"255. Anas reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said:\n"
        "He who wore silk in this world would not wear it in the Hereafter.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha256" >"256. Qatada said:\n"
        "We asked Anas b. Malik which garment did Allah's Messenger may peace be upon him) love or like (to wear). He said: The mantle of Yemen.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha257" >"257. A'isha reported that Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) went out one morning wearing a blanket made of (camel's or sheep's) black hair with patterns of camel saddles upon it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha258" >"258. A'isha reported that the bedding on which. Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) slept was made of leather stuffed with palm fibre.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha259" >"259. A'isha reported that the pillow on which Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) reclined was of leather stuffed with palm fibre.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha260" >"260. Jabir b. Abdullah reported:\n"
        "When I was married. Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) asked me if I had got carpets. I said: How can we have carpets? Thereupon he said: You will soon have. Jabir said: My wife had possessed a carpet, and I said to her to remove that away from me, but she would say: Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) had said: You will soon have.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha261" > "261. Ibn 'Umar reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) having said:\n"
        "Allah will not look upon him who trails his garment out of pride.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha262" > "262. Abu Huraira reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said that there was a person who used to walk with pride because of his thick hair and fine mantles. He was made to sink in the earth and he would go on sinking in the earth until the Last Hour would come.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha263" >"263. Abu Huraira reported that Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) forbade the wearing of gold signet ring.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha264" >"264. Anas b. Malik reported that Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) had made for him a silver ring. and got engraved on it (Muhammad, Messenger of Allah) and said to the people I have got made a ring of silver and engraved in it (these words) (Muhammad, Messenger of Allah). So none should engrave these (words) like this engravement.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha265" >"265. Anas reported that when Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) decided to write to the Kisra (the King of Persia), Caesar (Emperor of Rome), and the Negus (the Emperor of Abyssinia), it was said to him that they would not accept the letter without the seal over it; so Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) got a seal made, the ring of which was made of silver and there was engraved on it:\n"
        "\"Muhammad, the Messenger of Allah.\"(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha266" >"266. 'Ali reported:\n"
        "Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) forbade me that I should wear a ring in this and that finger of mine, and he pointed to the middle finger and the next one.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha267" >"267. Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "\"When one of you puts on sandals, he should first put in the right foot, and when he takes off he should take off the left one first. And he should wear both of them or take both off.\"(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha268" >"268. Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "None of you should walk in one sandal; either he should wear the two or should take off the two.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha269" >"269. Jabir reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) forbade that a man should eat with the left hand or walk with one sandal or wrap himself completely leaving no opening for the arms (to draw out) or support himself when sitting with a single garment wrapped round his knees which may expose his private parts.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha270" >"264. Jabir reported that when Abu Qubafa (father of Abu Bakr) came in the yeu of Victory or on the Day of Victory (to the Prophet to pledge his allegiance to him) his head and his beard were white like hyssop. He (the Holy Prophet) commaded or the women were commanded by him that they should change this with something (that the colour of his hair should be changed).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha271" > "265. Abu Horaira reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "The Jews and the Christians do not dye (their hair), so oppose them.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha272" >"266. Abu Talha reported:\n"
        "I heard Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying: Angels do not enter the house in which there is a dog or a statue.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha273" >"267. A'isha reported:\n"
        "Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) visited me. and I had a shelf with a thin cloth curtain hangin. over it and on which there were portraits. No sooner did he see it than he tore it and the colour of his face underwent a change and he said: A'isha, the most grievous torment from the Hand of Allah on the Day of Resurrection would be for those who imitate (Allah) in the act of His creation. A'isha said: We tore it into pieces and made a cushion or two cushions out of that.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha274" >"268. Ibn 'Umar reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) having said:\n"
        "Those who paint pictures would be punished on the Day of Resurrection and it would be said to them: Breathe soul into what you have created.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha275" >"275. Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri reported Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "Avoid sitting on the paths. They (his Companions) said: Allah's Messenger, there is no other help to it (but to sit there as we) hold our meetings and discuss matters there. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said: If you have to sit at all, then fulfil the rights, of the path. They said: What are their rights? Thereupon he said: Keeping the eye downward (so that you may not stare at the women), refraining from doing some harm to the other and exchanging mutual greetings (saying as-Salamu 'Alaikum to one another) and commanding the good and forbidding the evil.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha276" >"276. Asma', daughter of Abu Bakr, reported that a woman came to Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) and said:\n"
        "I have a daughter who has been newly wedded. She had an attack of smallpox and thus her hair had fallen; should I add false hair to her head? Thereupon Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said: Allah has cursed the woman who adds some false hair and the woman who asks for it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha277" >"277. Ibn Umar reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) cursing the woman who added false hair and the woman who asked for tattoos. This hadith has been reported on the authority of Abdullah through another chain of transmitters.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha278" >"278. Anas reported that person at Baqi' called another person as\" Abu'l- Qasim,\" and Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) turned towards him. He (the person who had uttered these words) said:\n"
        "Messenger of Allah, I did not mean you, but I called such and such (person), whereupon Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said: You may call yourself by my name, but not by my kunya.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha279" >"279. Samura b. Jundub reported:\n"
        "The Messenger of Allah (peace and blessings of Allah be upon him) said \"The dearest phrases to Allah are four: Subhan Allah (Hallowed be Allah), Al-Hamdulillah (Praise be to Allah), La ilaha illa-Allah (There is no deity but Allah), Allahu Akbar (Allah is Greater). There is no harm for you in which of them begin with (while remembering Allah). And do not give these names to your servants: Yasar and Rabah and Najih and Aflah.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha280" >"280. Ibn 'Umar reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) changed the name of 'Asiya (Disobedient) and said:\n"
        "You are Jamila (i. e. good and handsome). Ahmad (one of the narrators) narrated it with a slight variation of wording.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha281" >"281. Zainab, daughter of Umm Salama, reported:\n"
        "My name first was Barra. Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) gave me the name of Zainab. Then there entered (into the house of Allah's Prophet as a wife) Zainab, daughter of Jahsh, and her name was also Barra, and he gave her the name of Zainab.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha282" >"282. Anas b. Malik reported:\n"
        "I took 'Abdullah b. Abi Talha Ansari to Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) at the time of his birth. Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) was at that time wearing a woollen cloak and besmearing the camels with tar. He said: Have you got with you the dates? I said: Yes. He took hold of the dates and put them in his mouth and softened them, then opened the mouth of the infant and put that in it and the child began to lick it. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said: The Ansar have a liking for the dates, and he (the Holy Prophet) gave him the name of 'Abdullah.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha283" >"283. 'A'isha reported that the new-born infants were brought to Allah's Messenger (ﷺ). He blessed them and rubbed their palates with dates.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha284" >"284. Sahl b. Sa'd as-Sa'id reported that a person peeped through the hole of the door of Allah's Messenger (ﷺ), and at that time Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) had with him a scratching instrument with which he had been scratching his head. When Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) saw him. he said:\n"
        "If I were to know that you had been peeping through the door, I would have thrust that into your eyes, and Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said: Permission is needed as a protection against glance.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha285" >"285. Jarir b. 'Abdullah reported:\n"
        "I asked Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) about the sudden glance (that is cast) on the face (of a non-Mahram). He commanded me that I should turn away my eyes.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha286" >"286. Wathila b. al-Asqa' reported:\n"
        "I heard Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying: Verily Allah granted eminence to Kinana from amongst the descendants of Isma'il, and he granted eminence to the Quraish amongst Kinana, and he granted eminence to Banu Hashim amonsgst the Quraish, and he granted me eminence from the tribe of Banu Hashim.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha287" >"287. Jabir b. Samura reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "I recognise the stone in Mecca which used to pay me salutations before my advent as a Prophet and I recognise that even now.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha288" >"288. Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "I shall be pre-eminent amongst the descendants of Adam on the Day of Resurrection and I will be the first intercessor and the first whose intercession will be accepted (by Allah).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha289" >"289. Jabir reported that a person came to Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) and asked for food. And he gave him half a wasq of barley, and the person and his wife and their guests kept on making use of it (as a food) until he weighed it (in order to find out the actual quantity, and it was no more). He came to Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) (and informed him about it). He said:\n"
        "Had you not weighed it, you would be eating out of it and it would have remained intact for you.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha290" >"290. Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "The similitude of mine and that of my Umma is that of a person who lit fire and there began to fall into it insects and moths. And I am there to hold you back, but you plunge into it.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha291" >"291. Abu Musa reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "When Allah, the Exalted and Glorious, intends to show mercy to an Umma from amongst His servants He calls back His Apostle to his eternal home and makes him a harbinger and recompense in the world to come; and when He intends to cause destruction to an Umma, He punishes it while its Apostle is alive and He destroys it as he (the Apostle) witnesses it and he cools his eyes by destruction as they had belied him and disobeyed his command.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha292" >"292. Sahl (b. Sa'd) reported:\n"
        "I heard Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) as saying: I shall go to the Cistern before you and he who comes would drink and he who drinks would never feel thirsty, and there would come to me people whom I would know and who would know me. Then there would be intervention between me and them. Abu Hazim said that Nu'man b. Abu 'Ayyash heard it and I narrated to them this hadith, and said: Is it this that you heard Sahl saying? He said: Yes, and I bear witness to the fact that I heard it from Abu Sa'id Khudri also, but he made this addition that he (the Holy Prophet) would say: They are my followers, and it would be said to him: You do not know what they did after you and I will say to them: Woe to him who changes (his religion) after me.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha293" >"293. `Abdullah b. `Amr al-`As, reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "My Cistern (is as wide and broad that it requires) a month's journey (to go round it) all, and its sides are equal and its water is whiter than silver, and its odour is more fragrant than the fragrance of musk, and its jugs (placed around it) are like stars in the sky; and he who would drink from it would never feel thirsty after that. Asma', daughter of Abu Bakr said: Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) said: I would be on the Cistern so that I would be seeing those who would be coming to me from you, but some people would be detained (before reaching me). I would say: My Lord, they are my followers and belong to my Ummah, and it would be said to me: Do you know what they did after you? By Allah, they did not do good after you, and they turned back upon their heels. He (the narrator) said: lbn Abu Mulaika used to say (in supplication): O Allah, I seek refuge with Thee that we should turn back upon our heels or put to any trial about our religion.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha294" >"294. Uqba b. 'Amir reported Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) as saying:\n"
        "Allah's Messenger offered prayer over those who had fallen matyrs at Uhud. He then climbed the pulpit as if someone is saying good-bye to the living and the dead, and then said: I shall be there as your predecesor on the Cistern before you, and it is as wide as the distance between Aila and Juhfa (Aila is at the top of the gulf of 'Aqaba). I am not afraid that you would associate anything with Allah after me, but I am afraid that you may be (allured) by the world and (vie) with one another (in possessing material wealth) and begin killing one another, and you would be destroyed as were destroyed those who had gone before you. 'Uqba said that that was the last occasion that he saw Allah's Massenger on the pulpit.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha295" >"295. 'Amir b. Sa'd b. Abu Waqqas reported:\n"
        "I wrote (a letter) to Jabir b. Samura (and it was sent) through my servant Nafi' asking him to inform me about something (pertaining to the Haud Kauthar). He wrote to me: I heard him (the Holy Prophet) say: I shall be there ahead of you at the Haud Kauthar.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha296" > "296. Sa`d reported that on the Day of Uhud I saw on the right side of Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) and on his left side two persons dressed in white clothes and whom I did not see before nor after that, and they were Gabriel and Michael (Allah be pleased with both of them).(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha297" > "297. Anas b. Malik reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) was the sublimest among people (in character) and the most generous amongst them and he was the bravest of men. One night the people of Medina felt disturbed and set forth in the direction of a sound when Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) met them on his way back as he had gone towards that sound ahead of them. He was on the horse of Abu Talha which had no saddle over it, and a sword was slung round his neck, and he was saying:\n"
        "There was nothing to be afraid of, and he also said: We found it (this horse) like a torrent of water (indicating its swift-footedness), whereas the horse had been slow before that time.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha298" >"298. Ibn 'Abbas reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) was the most generous of people in charity, but he was generous to the utmost in the month of Ramadan. Gabriel (peace be upon him) would meet him every year during the month of Ramadin until it ended, and Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) recited to him the Qur'an; and when Gabriel met him Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) was most generous in giving charity like the blowing wind.(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha299" >"299. Anas b. Malik reported:\n"
        "I served the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) for ten years, and, by Allah, he never said to me any harsh word, and he never said to me about a thing as to why I had done that and as to why I had not done that. Abu Rabi' has made this addition (in this narration):\" The work which a servant should do.\" There is no mention of his words\" By Allah\".(sahih Muslim)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ha300" >"300. Anas reported that Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) had the best disposition amongst people. He sent me on an errand one day, and I said:\n"
        "By Allah, I would not go. I had, however, this idea in my mind that I would do as Allah's Apostle (ﷺ) had commanded me to do. I went out until I happened to come across children who had been playing in the street. In the meanwhile, Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) came there and he caught me by the back of my neck from behind me. As I looked towards him I found him smiling and he said: Unais, did you go where I commanded you to go? I said: Allah's Messenger, yes, I am going. Anas further said: I served him for nine years but I know not that he ever said to me about a thing which I had done why I did that, or about a thing I had left as to why I had not done that.(sahih Muslim)"
    </string>


</resources>