<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>



    <string name="hatme1" translatable="false">"What is khatma?\n"
        "\n"
        "Khatma-i hajagan is a kind of dhikr which specificly belongs to the tariqah of naqshabandiyya. So, it would be more benefical to give a little information about dhikr, before being informed about khatma-i hajagan.\n"
        "\n"
        "DHIKRULLAH\n"
        "\n"
        "Precious reader! You should also know that there are lots of verses in Qur'an al-kareem regarding dhikr. But here, we are going to try to explain the meanings of some verses regarding the main characteristic of dhikr and al-ahkaam of it.\n"
        "\n"
        "\"O you who have believed, remember Allah with much remembrance.And exalt Him morning and afternoon.\" 1\n"
        "\"So remember Me; I will remember you.\"  2\n"
        "\"...and remember Allah often that you may succeed.\"  3\n"
        "\n"
        "\"And when you have completed the prayer, remember Allah standing, sitting, or [lying] on your sides.\"   4\n"
        "\n"
        "\"O you who have believed, when you encounter a company [from the enemy forces], stand firm and remember Allah much that you may be successful.\"   5\n"
        "\n"
        "\"[Are] men whom neither commerce nor sale distracts from the remembrance of Allah and performance of prayer and giving of zakah. They fear a Day in which the hearts and eyes will [fearfully] turn about \"  6\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Indeed, the hypocrites [think to] deceive Allah, but He is deceiving them. And when they stand for prayer, they stand lazily, showing [themselves to] the people and not remembering Allah except a little\"   7\n"
        "\n"
        "\"And remember your Lord within yourself in humility and in fear without being apparent in speech - in the mornings and the evenings. And do not be among the heedless.\"   8\n"
        "\n"
        "\"...and the men who remember Allah often and the women who do so - for them Allah has prepared forgiveness and a great reward.\"   9\n"
        "\n"
        "Precious reader! let's read this hadith which is a bit of a long but also muttafaqoon alaihi carefully.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Al-Bukhaari (6408) and Muslim (2689) narrated from Abu Hurayrah that the Messenger of Allah (blessings and peace of Allah be upon him) said:\n"
        "\n"
        "“Allah, may He be blessed and exalted, has angels who travel about, with no other job but to seek out gatherings of dhikr. When they find a gathering in which Allah is remembered, they sit with them and encircle them with their wings, until they fill the space between earth and the first heaven. When they (the people) part, they (the angels) ascend to heaven and Allah, may He be glorified and exalted, asks them, although He knows best: ‘From where have you come?’ They say: ‘We have come from some of Your slaves on earth, who were glorifying You, magnifying You, proclaiming Your Oneness, praising You and asking of You.’ He says: ‘What are they asking of Me?’ They say: ‘They are asking You for Your Paradise.’ He says: ‘Have they seen My Paradise?’ They say: ‘No, O Lord.’ He says: ‘So how about if they saw My Paradise?’ They say: ‘And they are seeking Your protection.’ He says: ‘From what are they seeking My protection?’ They say: ‘From Your Fire, O Lord.’ He says: ‘Have they seen My Fire?’ They say: ‘No, O Lord.’ He says: ‘So how about if they saw My Fire?’ They say: ‘And they are asking You for forgiveness.’ He says: ‘I have forgiven them, and given them what they asked for, and granted them protection from that from which they sought My protection.’ They say: ‘Lord, among them is So and so, a sinner who was merely passing by, then he sat with them.’ He says: ‘Him too I have forgiven. They are people whose companion cannot be doomed.’”\n"
        "\n"
        "According to a report narrated by al-Bukhaari: “[Allah] says: ‘Have they seen Me?’ They say: ‘No, by Allah, they have not seen You.’ He says: ‘So how about if they saw Me?’ They say: ‘If they saw You, they would strive harder in worshipping You, and they would strive harder in lauding and praising You, and strive harder in glorifying You.’”  10\n"
        "\n"
        "KHATMA-İ HAJAGAN\n"
        "\n"
        "Precious reader! There is a specific kind of dhikr for each tariqah which they do according to their own usool. Dawran, Sama, Dhikr-i Qiyaam, Darb-i Asma and Khatma-i Hajagan are of the main kinds of dhikr. Here we are going to briefly inform about khatma-i hajagan and adabs of it which is specificly adopted by tariqah of naqshabandiyya.\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Hajagan\" is the plural form of the persian word \"haja\". lt means; shaikh, scholar, great ustaad. And khatma is the halaqa of dhikr, during which some surahs, verses, salaatu salaams and specific tasbihah are recited. So, khatma-i hajagan has beautiful meanings as dhikr of shaiks, dhikr of scholars, dhikr of great ustaads. Since this dhikr halaqa specificly belongs to the tariqah of naqshabandiyya, let's check out the opinions of the seniors of this path; our hodjas, shaikhs, ustaads, right after we inform you about the opinions of Khadrat Haja Bahauddeen Naqshaband (ks) after whom this tariqah is named.\n"
        "\n"
        "Shah-i Naqshaband (ks) says in his book called Maqamat-i Bahaiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"A mureed who starts sair-u sulook, makes most effort not to be deprived from majalees of khatma as well as he keeps doing his daily dhikr. Being with sadiqoon is a divine order. lf it's a spiritual gathering, it's called \"rabita\" which is one of the main principle of tasawoof. Khatm-i hajagan is togetherness both spiritually and phisically.\" ...11\n"
        "\n"
        "Description of khatma by Mawlana Khalid Baghdadi(ks):\n"
        "\n"
        "Firstly, al-istighfaar is recited 25 times. lt could be 5 or 15 times as well. Then eyes would be closed, concentrated on the heart doing rabita. Firstly, 7 Fatiha-i shareef are recited. then 100 salawaat-i shareefa, 79 surah inshirah, 1001 ikhlaas-i shareef, and again 7 fatiha-i shareefa and 100 salawaat-i shareefa and also ashr-i shareefa is recited and dua is done. Vukoof-i qalbi has to be paid heed all the time. ...12\n"
        "\n"
        "Description of khatma by Ahmad Dhiyauddeen Gumushhanawi (ks):\n"
        "\n"
        "The dhikr majlees which is done by the mureeds of naqshabandiyya and khalidiyya, by the permission and authority of their sheiks' is called \"khatma-i hajagan\". Firstly, the dhikr starts with istighfar by the sign of the mursheed. This could be 15 times or 5 times according to the will of the mursheed. Then eyes would be closed, concentrated on the heart doing rabita. Firstly, 7 Fatiha-i shareef are recited. then 100 salawaat-i shareefa, 79 surah inshirah, 1001 ikhlaas-i shareef, and again 7 fatiha-i shareefa and 100 salawaat-i shareefa and also ashr-i shareefa is recited and dua is done. As well as vukoof-i qalbi is paid heed during the khatm, the adab which the silsilah and the great meshayikhs are present in this majlees spiritually also has to be preserved. ...13\n"
        "\n"
        "KINDS OF KHATMA-I HAJAGAN\n"
        "\n"
        "Precious reader! There are three kinds of  khatma-i hajagan. Let's read these together in order now.\n"
        "\n"
        "1) Long Khatma;\n"
        "\n"
        "lf the jamaah is more than 10 people, or  there are at least 10 people who knows surah inshirah by heart except the imam, then long khatma would be done. During long khatma, 14 surah al-Fatihah, 200 salaats, 79 surah al-lnshirah, and 1001 lkhlas-i shareef would be recited in total. The order of this recitation is;\n"
        "\n"
        "1) 7 surah al-Fatihah\n"
        "\n"
        "2) 100 salaat\n"
        "\n"
        "3) 79 surah al-lnshirah\n"
        "\n"
        "4) 1001 surah al-lkhlaas\n"
        "\n"
        "5) 7 surah al-Fatihah\n"
        "\n"
        "6) 100 salaat    ...16\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "2) Short Khatma;\n"
        "\n"
        "lf the jamaah is less than 10 people or the people who knows surah al-lnshirah by heart except the imam are less than 10, then short khatma would be done. During short khatma, 14 surah al-Fatihah, 200 salaats, 500 times \"yaa Baqi, anta al-Baqi\" would be recited in total. Surah al-lnshirah or surah al-lkhlas wouldn't be recited. The order of this recitation is;\n"
        "\n"
        "1) 7 surah al-Fatihah\n"
        "\n"
        "2) 100 salaat\n"
        "\n"
        "3) 500 times \"yaa Baqi, anta al-Baqi\"\n"
        "\n"
        "4) 7 surah al-Fatihah\n"
        "\n"
        "5) 100 salaat   ...17\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "3) Khatma Of Al-Qalima At-Tawheed;\n"
        "\n"
        "The point which distincts the khatma of al-qalima  at-tawheed from the other kinds of khatma is that the imam doing the qalima-i tawheed dhikr during this khalaqa. Otherwise the number of the whole surahs and dhikr recited are the same.  ...18\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "THE ADAB OF KHATMA-I HAJAGAN\n"
        "\n"
        "Precious reader! lt's benefical to know that dhikrullah requires seriousness, just before we pass to the matters we are going to sort down now. Because, as always, Allahu Taala is your collocutor here. More respect has to be shown for Khaliq-i Zuljalaal than the respect shown for the teacher and the principle by the student at school, or for the commander by the soldier, or for the parents by the kids, or for the chief by the workers.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "1) Being upon wudoo by purifying himself from hadas and najasah.\n"
        "\n"
        "2) Being upon khushoo and peace, purifying the heart from the worldly thoughts and matters.\n"
        "\n"
        "3) Turning towards qiblah.\n"
        "\n"
        "4) Sitting on the right buttock with his  knees bent and both legs are conveniently positioned to the right side of his body or sitting on the knees unless there is a neccessity not to.\n"
        "\n"
        "5) lf it's a dhikr majlees, then sitting like a halaqa and make the knees touch eachother. Only the knees of the imam wouldn't be touched.\n"
        "\n"
        "6) Doing rabita of mawt, rabita of mursheed and rabita of qalb(peace).\n"
        "\n"
        "7) Wearing a good fragrance.\n"
        "\n"
        "8) Using miswaaq.\n"
        "\n"
        "9) Closing the eyes and stay that way till the dhikrullah is over. The riwayah of shaeeh-i Muslim regarding this is:\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Ali karramAllahu taala wajhah, asked Rasoolullah alaihissalatu wassalam to show him the shortest, the easiest and the most virtuous way to Allaah subhana wa taala.\n"
        "\n"
        "Sayyiduna Prophet alaihissalatu wassalaam said:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Yaa Ali! You should keep remembering Allahu taala during your khalwat and you are alone, during your jalwat and you are among people.\".  Hadrat Ali radiAllahu taala anhu asked:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"How would l remember Allahu taala, yaa Rasoolullah?\". Rasoolullah alaihissalatu wassalaam said:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Close your eyes and listen what l say 3 times. And then repeat it 3 times and let me hear.\".\n"
        "\n"
        "Sayyiduna Prophet alaihissalatu wassalaam closed his eyes and said \"Laa ilaaha illallaah\" thrice outloud. Hadrat Ali radiAllahu taala anhu was listening to him upon great khushoo. Then, Hadrat Ali radiAllahu anhu closed his eyes and said \"Laa ilaaha illallaah\" thrice outloud. Hadrat Prophet alaihissalatu wassalaam said: \"The most virtuous word which the previous prophets and l said is \"Laa ilaaha illallaah\". The hour will not be established as long as there would be people saying \"Allaah, Allaah,  Allaah.,,,\" on the earth.\" ...19\n"
        "\n"
        "11) Reciting surah al-Fatihah once and surah al-lkhlaas three times and gifting the ajr(reward) of it to the spirits of the seniors.\n"
        "\n"
        "12) Reciting the names of sadaat-i kiraam.\n"
        "\n"
        "13) Doing dhikrullaah in a closed and dark place and paying attention to keeping the door locked. The saheeh hadith in musnad of Ahmad lbn Hanbal regarding this matter is:\n"
        "\n"
        "According to Shaddaad bin Aws: \"While Hadrat Prophet alaihissalatu wassalaam sitting in his house with a group of sahabas, he said: \"lf there's any stranger among you, take him out and closed the door.\", we told that there is no stranger among us. After closing the door of hujra-i saadah we made dhikrullaah saying \"Laa ilaaha illallaah, laa ilaaha ilallaah,...\" outloud all together for a while.\".  ...20\n"
        "\n"
        "14) Trying not to loose himself, trying to hold himelf even in the condition of jazbah during dhikr.\n"
        "\n"
        "15) lf it's adhikr halaqa, not to raise his voice louder than the imam.\n"
        "\n"
        "16) Not to open the doors and turn the lights on right after the dhikrullaah ends.\n"
        "\n"
        "17) Turning to his own heart before turning to the worldly thought right after dhikrullaah ends.\n"
        "\n"
        "18) Definitely not to drink any water right after dhikrullaah ends.\n"
        "\n"
        "19) Not to hide his situation at the end of dhikrullaah from his mursheed.\n"
        "\n"
        "20) Not to let people who didn't give bi'at  to the shaikh in khatma.\n"
        "\n"
        "21) Using stones during khatma to hold count of the dhikr.\n"
        "\n"
        "THE SOURCES USED FOR ADAB\n"
        "\n"
        "1) Risala-i Khalidiyya and Risala of Adab-i Dhikr (Mawlana Khalid Baghdadi ks)\n"
        "\n"
        "2) Walees and The Usool in Tariqahs (Ahmad Dhiyauddeen Gumushhanawi ks)\n"
        "\n"
        "3) Gumushhanawi Ahmad Dhiyauddeen (lrfan Gunduz)\n"
        "\n"
        "4) Fatwas Regarding Tasawoof and Tariqahs (Umar Dhiyaudden Daghestani ks)\n"
        "\n"
        "6) Awrad-i Bahaiyya (compilet by Mehmet Veli Şen)\n"
        "\n"
        "7) Risala of Khatma-i Hajagan (Ömer Yıldız)\n"
        "\n"
        "8) Risala of Dhikr (Ömer Yıldız)\n"
        "\n"
        "NOTES\n"
        "\n"
        "1 (Ahzab/41-42)\n"
        "\n"
        "2 (Baqarah/152)\n"
        "\n"
        "3 (Jumuah/10)\n"
        "\n"
        "4 (Nisa/103)\n"
        "\n"
        "5 (Anfal/45)\n"
        "\n"
        "6 (Noor/37)\n"
        "\n"
        "7 (Nisa/142)\n"
        "\n"
        "8 (A'raf/205)\n"
        "\n"
        "9 (Ahzab/35)\n"
        "\n"
        "10 (Al-Lu'lu wal-Marjan v/3 p/278*279 H.Nr/1722) Muhammad Fuad Abdulbaqi\n"
        "\n"
        "11 (Risalah of Khatma-i Hajagan p. 8-9) Ömer Yıldız\n"
        "\n"
        "12 (Risala-i Khalidiyya and Risala of Adab-i Dhikr p. 61-62) Mawlana Khalid Baghdadi ks Translator: Mehmed Zahid Kotku\n"
        "\n"
        "13 (Gumushhanawi Ahmad Dhiyauddeen p. 274) lrfan Gündüz\n"
        "\n"
        "13 (lskam, Love and Tasawoof p. 103-104) Mahmud Es'ad Coşan\n"
        "\n"
        "15 (Awrad-i Bahaiyya p. 23) Compilor: Mehmed  Veli Şen\n"
        "\n"
        "16 (Risalah of Dhikr p. 165-Risalah of Khatma-i Hajagan p.84-86) Ömer Yıldız\n"
        "\n"
        "17 (Risalah of Dhikr p. 165-Risalah of Khatma-i Hajagan p.84-86) Ömer Yıldız\n"
        "\n"
        "18 (Awrad-i Bahaiyya p. 24) Compilor: Mehmed  Veli Şen\n"
        "\n"
        "19 (Fatwas Regarding Tasawoof and Tariqahs p.65-66) Umar Dhiyaudden Daghestani ks\n"
        "\n"
        "20 (Fatwas Regarding Tasawoof and Tariqahs p.67-68) Umar Dhiyaudden Daghestani ks"

</string>




</resources>
