<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>


    <string name="fatiha">"Surah al-Fatiha\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Alhamdu lillaahi Rabbil 'aalameen\n"
        "Ar-Rahmaanir-Raheem\n"
        "Maaliki Yawmid-Deen\n"
        "Iyyaaka na'budu wa lyyaaka nasta'een\n"
        "Ihdinas-Siraatal-Mustaqeem\n"
        "Siraatal-lazeena an'amta 'alaihim ghayril-maghdoobi 'alaihim wa lad-daaalleen\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "In the name of Allah, Most Gracious, Most Merciful.\n"
        "Praise be to Allah, the Cherisher and Sustainer of the worlds;\n"
        "Most Gracious, Most Merciful;\n"
        "Master of the Day of Judgment.\n"
        "Thee do we worship, and Thine aid we seek.\n"
        "Show us the straight way,\n"
        "The way of those on whom Thou hast bestowed Thy Grace, those whose (portion) is not wrath, and who go not astray.\n"
        "\n"
  </string>

    <string name="nas">"Surah an-Nas\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Qul a'uzu birabbin naas\n"
        "Malikin naas\n"
        "Ilaahin naas\n"
        "Min sharril was waasil khannaas\n"
        "Al lazee yuwas wisu fee sudoorin naas\n"
        "Minal jinnati wan naas (End Juz 30)\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Say: I seek refuge with the Lord and Cherisher of Mankind,\n"
        "The King (or Ruler) of Mankind,\n"
        "The Allah (for judge) of Mankind,-\n"
        "From the mischief of the Whisperer (of Evil), who withdraws (after his whisper),-\n"
        "(The same) who whispers into the hearts of Mankind,-\n"
        "Among Jinns and among men.\n"
        "\n"</string>

    <string name="felak"> "Surah al-Falaq\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Qul a'uzoo bi rabbil-falaq\n"
        "Min sharri ma khalaq\n"
        "Wa min sharri ghasiqin iza waqab\n"
        "Wa min sharrin-naffaa-saati fil 'uqad\n"
        "Wa min shar ri haasidin iza hasad\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Say: I seek refuge with the Lord of the Dawn\n"
        "From the mischief of created things;\n"
        "From the mischief of Darkness as it overspreads;\n"
        "From the mischief of those who practise secret arts;\n"
        "And from the mischief of the envious one as he practises envy\n"
        "\n"</string>


    <string name="ihlas"> "Surah al-Ikhlaas\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Qul huwal laahu ahad\n"
        "Allah hus-samad\n"
        "Lam yalid wa lam yoolad\n"
        "Wa lam yakul-lahu kufuwan ahad\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Say: He is Allah, the One and Only;\n"
        "Allah, the Eternal, Absolute;\n"
        "He begetteth not, nor is He begotten;\n"
        "And there is none like unto Him.\n"
        "\n"</string>

    <string name="tebbet"> "Surah al-Lahab\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Tab bat yadaa abee Lahabinw-wa tabb\n"
        "Maa aghna 'anhu maaluhu wa ma kasab\n"
        "Sa yas laa naran zaata lahab\n"
        "Wam ra-atuhu hamma latal-hatab\n"
        "Fee jeediha hab lum mim-masad\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Perish the hands of the Father of Flame! Perish he!\n"
        "No profit to him from all his wealth, and all his gains!\n"
        "Burnt soon will he be in a Fire of Blazing Flame!\n"
        "His wife shall carry the (crackling) wood - As fuel!-\n"
        "A twisted rope of palm-leaf fibre round her (own) neck!\n"
        "\n"</string>



    <string name="nasr">"Surah an-Nasr\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Iza jaa-a nas rullahi walfath\n"
        "Wa ra-aitan naasa yadkhuloona fee deenil laahi afwajah\n"
        "Fa sab bih bihamdi rabbika was taghfir, innahu kaana tawwaaba\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "When comes the Help of Allah, and Victory,\n"
        "And thou dost see the people enter Allah.s Religion in crowds,\n"
        "Celebrate the praises of thy Lord, and pray for His Forgiveness: For He is Oft-Returning (in Grace and Mercy).\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="kafirun">"Surah al-Kafirun\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Qul yaa-ai yuhal kaafiroon\n"
        "Laa a'budu ma t'abudoon\n"
        "Wa laa antum 'aabidoona maa a'bud\n"
        "Wa laa ana 'abidum maa 'abattum\n"
        "Wa laa antum 'aabidoona ma a'bud\n"
        "Lakum deenukum wa liya deen.\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Say : O ye that reject Faith!\n"
        "I worship not that which ye worship,\n"
        "Nor will ye worship that which I worship.\n"
        "Nor will I worship those whom you have worshipped;,\n"
        "Nor will ye worship that which I worship.\n"
        "To you be your Way, and to me mine.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="kevser">"Surah al-Kauthar\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Innaa a'taina kal kauthar\n"
        "Fa salli li rabbika wanhar\n"
        "Inna shani-aka huwal abtar\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "To thee have We granted the Fount (of Abundance).\n"
        "Therefore to thy Lord turn in Prayer and Sacrifice.\n"
        "For he who hateth thee, he will be cut off (from Future Hope)\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="maun">"Surah al-Ma'un\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Ara-aital lazee yu kazzibu bid deen\n"
        "Fa zaalikal lazi yadu'ul-yateem\n"
        "Wa la ya huddu 'alaa ta'amil miskeen\n"
        "Fa wai lul-lil mu salleen\n"
        "Al lazeena hum 'an salaatihim sahoon\n"
        "Al lazeena hum yuraa-oon\n"
        "Wa yamna'oonal ma'oon\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Seest thou one who denies the Judgment (to come)?\n"
        "Then such is the (man) who repulses the orphan (with harshness),\n"
        "And encourages not the feeding of the indigent.\n"
        "So woe to the worshippers\n"
        "Who are neglectful of their prayers,\n"
        "Those who (want but) to be seen (of men),\n"
        "But refuse (to supply) (even) neighbourly needs\n"
        "\n"</string>


    <string name="fil"> "Surah al-Fil\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Alam tara kaifa fa'ala rabbuka bi ashaabil feel\n"
        "Alam yaj'al kai dahum fee tad leel\n"
        "Wa arsala 'alaihim tairan abaabeel\n"
        "Tar meehim bi hi jaaratim min sij jeel\n"
        "Faja 'alahum ka'asfim m'akool\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Seest thou not how thy Lord dealt with the Companions of the Elephant?\n"
        "Did He not make their treacherous plan go astray?\n"
        "And He sent against them Flights of Birds,\n"
        "Striking them with stones of baked clay.\n"
        "Then did He make them like an empty field of stalks and straw, (of which the corn) has been eaten up.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="kureyş">"Surah al-Quraish\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Li-ilaafi quraish\n"
        "Elaafihim rihlatash shitaa-i wass saif\n"
        "Fal y'abudu rabba haazal-bait\n"
        "Allazi at'amahum min ju'inw-wa-aamana hum min khawf\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "For the covenants (of security and safeguard enjoyed) by the Quraish,\n"
        "Their covenants (covering) journeys by winter and summer,-\n"
        "Let them adore the Lord of this House,\n"
        "Who provides them with food against hunger, and with security against fear (of danger).\n"
        "\n"</string>

    <string name="asr">"Surah al-Asr\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Wal' asr\n"
        "Innal insaana lafee khusr\n"
        "Il lal lazeena aamanu wa 'amilus saali haati wa tawa saw bil haqqi wa tawa saw bis sabr\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "By (the Token of) Time (through the ages),\n"
        "Verily Man is in loss,\n"
        "Except such as have Faith, and do righteous deeds, and (join together) in the mutual teaching of Truth, and of Patience and Constancy.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="kadir">"Surah al-Qadr\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "Innaa anzalnaahu fee lailatil qadr\n"
        "Wa maa adraaka ma lailatul qadr\n"
        "Lailatul qadri khairum min alfee shahr\n"
        "Tanaz zalul malaa-ikatu war roohu feeha bi izni-rab bihim min kulli amr\n"
        "Salaamun hiya hattaa mat la'il fajr\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Verily! We have sent it (this Qur'an) down in the night of Al-Qadr (Decree)\n"
        "And what will make you know what the night of Al-Qadr (Decree) is?\n"
        "The night of Al-Qadr (Decree) is better than a thousand months (i.e. worshipping Allah in that night is better than worshipping Him a thousand months, i.e. 83 years and 4 months).\n"
        "Therein descend the angels and the Ruh [Jibrael (Gabriel)] by Allah's Permission with all Decrees,\n"
        "Peace! (All that night, there is Peace and Goodness from Allah to His believing slaves) until the appearance of dawn\n"
        "\n"</string>


    <string name="kunut1">"Dua Qunut (to be recited in Witr Prayer) \n"
        "\n"
        " Transliteration:\n"
        "Allah humma inna nast'eenuka wa nastaghfiruka wa nu'minu bika wa natawak-kalu 'alayka wa nuthne 'alayk-al khayr. Wa nashkuruka wa laaa nakfuruka wa nakhla'u wa natruku man-y yafjuruka. Allah humma iyyaka na'budu wa laka nusal-lee wa nasjudu wa ilayka nas'a wa nahfidu wa narju rahmataka wa nakhsha 'azabaka inna 'azabaka bil kuf-fari mulhiq.\n"
        "\n"
        "Translation:\n"
        "\n"
        "Oh Allah, we ask you for help and seek your forgiveness, and we believe in You and have trust in You, and we praise you in the best way and we thank You and we are not ungrateful to you, and we forsake and turn away from the one who disobeys you. O Allah, we worship You only and pray to You and prostrate ourselves before You, and we run towards You and serve You, and we hope to receive your mercy, and we fear your punishment. Surely, the disbelievers will receive your punishement.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="kunut2">\n\nAllâhümme iyyâke nabüdü\n\nve leke nüsallî ve nescüdü\n\nve ileyke nesâ ve nahfidü\n\nnercû rahmeteke\n\nve nahşâ azâbeke\n\ninne azâbeke bilküffâri mülhıg.\n\nAnlamı:\n\nAllahım ! Biz yalnız Sana kulluk ederiz.\n\nNamazı yalnız Senin için kılarız, ancak Sana secde ederiz.\n\nYalnız Sana koşar ve Sana yaklaştıracak şeyleri kazanmaya\n\nçalışırız. Rahmetinin devamını ve çoğalmasını dileriz.\n\nAzabından korkarız, şüphesiz Senin azabın kâfirlere ve inançsızlara ulaşır.ız."</string>
    <string name="salli"> "Salat Alan-Nabi (Darud) - Salutation to the Prophet(Salli barik salavatları)\n"
        "\n"
        "Transliteration:\n"
        "\n"
        "Allah humma sal-li 'ala Muhammadin\n"
        "wa 'ala ali Muhammadin,\n"
        "Kama sal-layta 'ala Ibraheema\n"
        "Wa'ala ali Ibraheema\n"
        "innaka Hameedum Majeed\n"
        "\n
         "Translation:\n"
        "\n"
        "Oh Allah, send grace and honour on Muhammad and\n"
        "On the family and true followers of Muhammad\n"
        "just as you sent Grace and Honour on Ibrahim\n"
        "and on the family and true followers of Ibrahim\n"
        "Surely, you are praiseworthy, the Great.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="barik"> "Allah humma barik 'ala Muhammadin\n"
        "wa 'ala ali Muhammadin,\n"
        "Kama barakta 'ala Ibraheema\n"
        "Wa 'ala ali Ibraheema\n"
        "innaka Hameedum Majeed.\n"
        "\n"
        "Oh Allah, send your blessing on Muhammad and\n"
        "the true followers of Muhammad, just\n"
        "as you sent blessings on Ibrahim\n"
        "and his true followers\n"
        "Surely, you are praiseworthy, the Great.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="ettahiyati">"Tashahud(Tahiyyat)\n"
        "\n"
        "Transliteration: \n"
        "\n"
        "At-tahiy-yatu lil-lahi was sala-watu wat-tay yibatu\n"
        "As-salamu 'alayka ay-yuhan-nabiy-yu\n"
        "wa rahma tullahi wa bara-katuhu\n"
        "As-salamu 'alayna wa'ala 'ibadil-la his-sali-heen\n"
        "Ash hadu al-la ilaha il-lal lahu\n"
        "wa ash hadu an-na Muhammadan\n"
        "'ab-duhu wa rasuluh.\n"
        "\n"
        "Translation:\n"
        "\n"
        "All compliments, all physical prayer,\n"
        "and all monitary worship are for Allah.\n"
        "Peace be upon you, Oh Prophet,\n"
        "and Allah's mercy and blesings.\n"
        "Peace be on us and on all righteous slaves of Allah.\n"
        "I bear witness that no one is worthy of worship except Allah\n"
        "And I bear witness that Muhammad is His slave and Messenger.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="rabbaneatina"> "Rabbana Atina\n"
        "\n"
        "Our Lord! Grant us good in this world and good in the hereafter, and save us from the chastisement of the fire [2:201]\n"
        "\n"
        "Rabbana atina fid-dunya hasanatan wa fil 'akhirati hasanatan waqina 'adhaban-nar \n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="rabbanefirli">"Rabbanaghfirli\n"
        "\n"
        "O our Lord! Cover (us) with Thy Forgiveness - me, my parents, and (all) Believers, on the Day that the Reckoning will be established! [14:41]\n"
        "\n"
        "Rabbana ghfir li wa li wallidayya wa lil Mu'mineena yawma yaqumul hisaab \n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="subhaneke">"Dua Al-Istiftah (Supplication of Starting) Recited only in the first Rakath(Subhaneke duası)\n"
        "\n"
        "Transliteration: Subhana Kal-lah hum-ma wabi hamdika wata-bara kasmuka wata'ala jad-duka wala ilaha ghyruka.\n"
        "\n"
        "Translation: Glory be to you, O Allah, and all praises are due unto you, and blessed is your name and high is your majesty and none is worthy of worship but you.\n"
        "\n"</string>


    <string name="ayetelkursi">"Ayat al-Kursi\n"
        "\n"
        "Bismillaahir Rahmaanir Raheem\n"
        "\n"
        "Allahu laaa ilaaha illaa huwal haiyul qai-yoom; laa taakhuzuhoo sinatunw wa laa nawm; lahoo maa fissamaawaati wa maa fil ard; man zallazee yashfa'u indahooo illaa be iznih; ya'lamu maa baina aideehim wa maa khalfahum; wa laa yuheetoona beshai 'immin 'ilmihee illa be maa shaaaa; wasi'a kursiyyuhus samaa waati wal arda wa la ya'ooduho hifzuhumaa; wa huwal aliyyul 'azeem  \n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Allah! There is no god but He - the Living, The Self-subsisting, Eternal. No slumber can seize Him Nor Sleep. His are all things In the heavens and on earth. Who is there can intercede In His presence except As he permitteth? He knoweth What (appeareth to His creatures As) Before or After or Behind them. Nor shall they compass Aught of his knowledge Except as He willeth. His throne doth extend Over the heavens And on earth, and He feeleth No fatigue in guarding And preserving them, For He is the Most High. The Supreme (in glory).\"  \n"
        "\n"
        "Amanar Rasoolu(Last two verses of Surah al-Baqarah)\n"
        " \n"
        "Aamanar-Rasoolu bimaaa unzila ilaihi mir-Rabbihee walmu'minoon; kullun aamana billaahi wa Malaaa'ikathihee wa Kutubhihee wa Rusulih laa nufarriqu baina ahadim-mir-Rusulihee wa qaaloo sami'naa wa ata'naa ghufraanaka Rabbanaa wa ilaikal-maseer\n"
        "Laa yukalliful-laahu nafsan illaa wus'ahaa; lahaa maa kasabat wa 'alaihaa maktasabat; Rabbanaa la tu'aakhiznaa in naseenaaa aw akhtaanaa; Rabbanaa wa laa tahmil-'alainaaa isran kamaa hamaltahoo 'alal-lazeena min qablinaa; Rabbanaa wa laa tuhammilnaa maa laa taaqata lanaa bih wa'fu 'annaa waghfir lanaa warhamnaa; Anta mawlaanaa fansurnaa 'alal qawmil kaafireen (section 40)\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "285. The Messenger believeth in what hath been revealed to him from his Lord, as do the men of faith. Each one (of them) believeth in Allah, His angels, His books, and His apostles. \"We make no distinction (they say) between one and another of His apostles.\" And they say: \"We hear, and we obey: (We seek) Thy forgiveness, our Lord, and to Thee is the end of all journeys.\"\n"
        "\n"
        "286. On no soul doth Allah Place a burden greater than it can bear. It gets every good that it earns, and it suffers every ill that it earns. (Pray:) \"Our Lord! Condemn us not if we forget or fall into error; our Lord! Lay not on us a burden Like that which Thou didst lay on those before us; Our Lord! Lay not on us a burden greater than we have strength to bear. Blot out our sins, and grant us forgiveness. Have mercy on us. Thou art our Protector; Help us against those who stand against faith.\" \n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="haşr"> "(Last 3 verses of) Surah al-Hashr\n"
        "\n"
        " \n"
        "Huwal-laahul-lazee laaa Ilaaha illaa Huwa 'Aalimul Ghaibi wash-shahaada; Huwar Rahmaanur-Raheem\n"
        "Huwal-laahul-lazee laaa Ilaaha illaa Huwal-Malikul Quddoosus-Salaamul Muminul Muhaiminul-'aAzeezul Jabbaarul-Mutakabbir; Subhaanal laahi 'Ammaa yushrikoon\n"
        "Huwal Laahul Khaaliqul Baari 'ul Musawwir; lahul Asmaaa'ul Husnaa; yusabbihu lahoo maa fis samaawaati wal ardi wa Huwal 'Azeezul Hakeem\n"
        "\n"
        "MEANING:\n"
        "Abdullah Yusuf Ali Translation\n"
        "Allah is He, than Whom there is no other god;- Who knows (all things) both secret and open; He, Most Gracious, Most Merciful.\n"
        "Allah is He, than Whom there is no other god;- the Sovereign, the Holy One, the Source of Peace (and Perfection), the Guardian of Faith, the Preserver of Safety, the Exalted in Might, the Irresistible, the Supreme: Glory to Allah. (High is He) above the partners they attribute to Him.\n"
        "He is Allah, the Creator, the Evolver, the Bestower of Forms (or Colours). To Him belong the Most Beautiful Names: whatever is in the heavens and on earth, doth declare His Praises and Glory: and He is the Exalted in Might, the Wise.\n"
        "\n"</string>
    <string name="anenarrasulü" translatable="false">"Okunuşu:\n\nAmenerrasulü bima ünzile ileyhi mirrabbihi vel mü’minun, \n\nküllün amene billahi vemelaiketihi ve kütübihi ve rusülih,\n\nla nüferriku beyne ehadin min rusülih, \n\nve kalu semi’na ve ata’na gufraneke rabbena ve ileykelmesir.\n\nLa yükellifullahü nefsenilla vüs’aha,\n\nleha ma kesebet ve aleyha mektesebet,\n\nrabbena latüahızna innesiyna ev ahta’na,\n\nrabbena vela tahmil aleyna ısran kema hameltehü alelleziyne min gablina,\n\nrabbena vela tühammilna, mala takatelena bih,\n\nva’fü anna, vağfirlena, verhamna, \n\nente mevlana fensurna alel gavmil kafiriyn.\n\nANLAMI:\n\nO peygamber de kendisine Rabbinden indirilene iman etti, \n\nMü’minler de (onlardan) her biri Allah’a, onun meleklerine, kitaplarına, peygamberlerine inandı.\n\n’‘Onun (Allah’ın) peygamberlerinden hiç birini diğerlerinin arkasından ayırmayız (hepsine inanırız), dinledik, (kabul ettik) emrine itaat ettik,\n\nEy Rabbimiz, mağfiretini isteriz.\n\nSon varışımız ancak sanadır’‘ dediler.\n\nAllah hiç kimseye gücünün yeteceğinden başkasını yüklemez. \n\n99Herkesin kazandığı hayır faidesine, yaptığı şer kendi zararınadır.\n\n‘‘Ey Rabbimiz, unuttuk, yahut yanıldıysak bizi tutup sorguya çekme. \n\nEy Rabbimiz, bizden evvelki ümmetlere yüklediğin gibi üstümüze ağır bir yük yükleme,\n\nEy Rabbimiz takat getiremeyeceğimizi bize taşıtma. Bizden sadır olan günahları sil, bağışla, bizi esirge. \n\nSen mevlamızsın bizim. Artık kâfirler ruhuna karşı bize yardım et.\n\n"</string>
    <string name="amentü">  "Amantu\n"
        "\n"
        "Amantu billahi wa malaikatihi wa kutubihi wa rusulihi wal-yawmil-akhiri wa bil-qadari khayrihi wa sharrihi minallahi taala wal-ba’thu ba’dal-mawti haqqun ashhadu an la ilaha illallah wa ashhadu anna Muhammadan abduhu wa rasuluh.\n"
        "\n"
        "Its meaning is as follows:\n"
        "\n"
        "Amantu billahi: I believed in the existence and oneness of Allah, that He has no partners or counterparts, that He has all kinds of loftiness and that He is free of all kinds of deficiency.\n"
        "\n"
        "Wa malaikatihi: I also believed in the angels of Allah.\n"
        "\n"
        "Wa kutubihi: I also believed in the books of Allah.\n"
        "\n"
        "Wa rusulihi: I also believed in the prophets of Allah.\n"
        "\n"
        "Wal-yawmil-akhiri: I also believed in the Day of Judgment.\n"
        "\n"
        "Wa bil-qadari khayrihi wa sharrihi minallahi taala: I also believed in the destiny, that everything that seems as good or evil to us take place through the knowledge, law and creation of Allah. \n"
        "\n"
        "Wal-ba’thu ba’dal-mawti haqqun: I also heartily believed in life after death (and resurrection). All of them are true and right.  \n"
        "\n"
        "Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah wa ashhadu anna Muhammadan abduhu wa rasuluh: I witness that there is no god but Allah and I witness that Hazrat Muhammad is his slave and messenger.\n"
        "\n"
        "The last sentence is called the word of Shahadah, that is, the sentence of witnessing."</string>


</resources>