<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">


    <string name="tarikat1" >Naqshabandies</string>
    <string name="tarikat2" >Qadiriyya</string>
    <string name="tarikat3" >Mawlawiyya</string>
    <string name="tarikat4" >Shazaliyya</string>
    <string name="tarikat5" >Wafaaiyya</string>
    <string name="tarikat6" >Badawiyya</string>
    <string name="tarikat7" >Malaamiyya</string>
    <string name="tarikat8" >Rifaiya</string>
    <string name="tarikat9" >Cerrahiyye</string>

    <string name="tarikat11" >Uşşakiler</string>
    <string name="tarikat12" >Kadiri-Rufai</string>
    <string name="tarikat13" >Halvetiler</string>



    <string name="naksi1" >What,s Naqshabandiyya?</string>
    <string name="naksi2" >Basis</string>
    <string name="naksi3" >Golden Chain</string>
    <string name="naksi4" >11 Candles</string>

    <string name="kadiri1" >Admittion of Tariqah</string>
    <string name="kadiri2" >Basis of Qadiriyya</string>
    <string name="kadiri3" >Chain</string>
    <string name="kadiri4" >Abdulqaadir Gilani and Qadiriyya</string>
    <string name="kadiri5" >Titles and Books</string>


    <string name="mevlevi1" >Mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi and Mawlawiyya</string>
    <string name="mevlevi2" >Basis</string>
    <string name="mevlevi3" >Tomb of Mawlana</string>
    <string name="mevlevi4" >Jami Mawlawi Ceremony</string>


    <string name="sazeli1" >Abu Hasal Shazali and Shazaliyya</string>
    <string name="sazeli2" >Basis</string>
    <string name="sazeli3" >Footnote</string>
    <string name="sazeli4" >Branches of Shazaliyya</string>


    <string name="bedeviye1" >Ahmad Badawi and Badawiyya</string>
    <string name="bedeviye2" >Initiation of the Tariqah</string>
    <string name="bedeviye3" >Chain</string>


    <string name="melami1" >The History of Malaamiyya  </string>
    <string name="vefai1" >The History of  Wafaaiyya</string>


    <string name="rufai1" >Ahmad Rifai and Rifaiya</string>
    <string name="rufai2" >Oh Grandfather! As-salamu Alaika</string>
    <string name="rufai3" >His Work</string>
    <string name="rufai4" >Branches of  Rifaiyya</string>
    <string name="rufai5" >Basis</string>
    <string name="rufai6" >Chain</string>


    <string name="rufai1text" >"Ahmad Rifa'i and Rifa'iya\n"
        "\n"
        "Rifa'iya, which is one of the first occured tariqahs was founded by Ahmad ar- Rifa'i, whose real name was Ahmad bin Ali al-Makki bin Yahya, The silsilah(lineage) of Ahmad ar- Rifa'i who is one of the Aqtaab-i Arbaa(the four qutbs), goes upto Hadrat Ali(ra).\n"
        "\n"
        "Ahmad ar- Rifa'i was born in Basra in 512/1118. He is sayyeed for his lineage goes uptı Hadrat Ali(ra) through Hadrat Hussain(ra). He was educated by his uncle Abu Baqr al-Ansari al-Vasiti who was a shaikh, when his father Sultan Ali passed away when he was 7 years old.He came to the fore in fiqh, hadees and tafseer ilms, he was given icazah(permission to teach) on these ilms.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat  Rifa'i, wore his darwish coat by the hand of :Shaikh Aliyyu'l Qari al-Vasiti. He entitled him as \"Abu'l Alamain\", to show that he knows zaheer and baatin ilms. This title was also showing that he had the degree of qutb and ghaws. After that he returned to his village and setteled down in the takkah which belonged to  his father. With his shaikh passing away in 539/1144, he continued the halaqa(ilm and dhikr gatherings) of his uncle Mansoor al-Bataihi. He entitled his nephew as \"shaikh of the shaiks\" and he gave him khilafah by giving him his own title \"the shaikh of all the zawiyas\" and he told him to settle down in his zawiya which is in Umm Abidah.\n"
        "\n"
        "Ahl al-hasad(people of jealousy) who couldn't tolerate his everyday increasing mureeds, complained about him to the khalifa of Abbasid, al-Muqtafi li-Amrillah saying bıth men and women were mixed in his dhikr halaqas. Khalifah assigned an inspector immediately. The person who was assigned composed such report upon his investigation:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"If this Sayyeed and his mureeds are upon a path other than sunnah(the path of Hadrat Muhammad Sallallahu alaihi wa sallam's), this means that there's no society who are following suah remained on earth.\"\n"
        "\n"
        "Khalifah apologized him by writing a letter to the shaikh, after checking up on the report."




</string>


    <string name="rufai2text" >"Oh Grandfather! As-salamu Alaika\n"
        "\n"
        "Rasoolullah(saw) Giving His Hand Out Of His Tomb\n"
        "\n"
        "Ahmad ar- Rifa'i went for pigrimage seven times. He made his first visit with lots of mureeds by his side in 555/1160.  It's said that he was replied from the tomb \"wa alaika oh my son\", when he came by the tomb of our Prophet(saw), he greeted him saying \"Oh Grandfather! As-salamu alaika\".\n"
        "\n"
        "Then he said a quatrain which means:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Oh Rasulalllah!, l used to send my soul to your sacred tomb during the times my body was far from you. Give your sacred hand to öe to kiss, so that my lips would taste the pleasure.\"\n"
        "\n"
        "Thereupon it's narrated that a hand came out of the tomb, Hadrat  Rifa'i kissed that hand, this was seen by shaikh Hayaat bin Qays Harrani, shaikh Adiyy bin Musaafir, Abdulqaadir Jilaani and shaikh Uqayl Manbiji.\n"
        "\n"
        "\"That colossal favour occured during the  majlees of conversation and acceptance\n"
        "Rasool offered his hand from his honorable tomb\n"
        "Mohammad Mostafaa caused blessings hand to hand\n"
        "No person was worthy of reaching such greatness\"\n"
</string>


    <string name="rufai3text" >"His Work\n"
        "\n"
        "Sharhu't Tanbeeh, Al-Hiqam ar-Rufaiyya, al-Burhaanu'l Muayyad, al-Majaleesu's-saniyya, al-Arbauna Hadeesan, Haalatu Ahli'l-Haqiqah Maallah, an-Nizaamu'l-Has li Ahli'l Ehtisas, al-Ash'ar, al-Ahzaab ve'l-Awraad.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "He prayed against a great calamity which was gonna befall onto society as \"Oh Allah! Make me as a roof for the calamity which is gonna befall onto the people, let what's coming come onto me\". He bought calamity in exchange of the rest of his life. He laid low with illness. Said \"My Rabb promissed me, not to meet Him in the flesh of dunia\" years ago. His words came true. There were no flesh remained in his body due to his illness, even his bone marrows were drained. He passed away in 578/1182. He was burried to Hanqah in baghdaad"
</string>


    <string name="rufai5text" >"Basis\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Rifa'i explains the basis of the tariqah as:\n"
        "\n"
        "Not demanding\n"
        "Not rejecting\n"
        "Not saving(money or such)\n"
        "\n"
        "\"My path is nothing but deen without bid'ah, deeds without laziness, niyyah(intention) without mischief, truthfullness without lies, status without hypocricy, degrees without demanding, thinking or claiming and full tawaqool to Allaah Subhana wa Taala.\".\n"
        "\n"
        "Samarrai writes that tariqah of  Rifa'iyya depends on these basis:\n"
        "\n"
        "Faith in the oneness of Allaah Subhana wa Taala\n"
        "Knowing Qur'an as the source of responsibilities\n"
        "Sticking to the sunnah of our Prophet(saw)\n"
        "Doing dhikr ang listenning to the innerself all the time\n"
        "Love\n"
        "Sticking to the system of faith which is framed by senior islaam ulamaa\n"
        "Respecting the Sahabas(ra) of our Prophet(saw)\n"
        "Faith in destiny, good and bad is all from Allaah Subhana wa Taala\n"
        "Tafaqoor\n"
        "Outloud dhikr with brothers\n"
        "Hawing the akhlaaq of Hadrat Mohammad(saw)\n"
        "Persuing islamic knowledge\n"
        "Reciting Qur'an all the time\n"
        "Avoiding fame\n"
        "Leaving unnecessary speeches\n"
        "Avoiding bida'ahs\n"
        "\n"
        "Mustafa Kara explains the basis of this tariqah as:\n"
        "\n"
        "Obeying the orders of Allaah Subhana wa Taala, avoiding what is forbidden\n"
        "Avoiding what's against shariah and tariqah\n"
        "Being steady in deen and promise\n"
        "Learning ilm and applying it\n"
        "Not digging into the flaws and faults of people\n"
        "Showing mercy to the needy\n"
        "Leaving bad habbits\n"
        "Taking the advices of the shaih\n"
        "\n"
        "The first dhikr which is given to the mureed by the mursheed is \"laa ilaaha illAllaah\". Later on Rahmaan, Raheem, Wahhaab, Quddoos, Haqq, Haleem, Hannaan, Hayy, Hafidh, Hameed names would be given.\n"
        "\n"
        "To beautify the akhlaaq, two  types of khawah(seclusion) is done, which are called khilafah and muharramiyyah. During this khalwah, mureed fasts.  Rifa'iyyas put a black  turban on."
</string>
    <string name="rufai4text" >"Branches of  Rifa'iyya\n"
        "\n"
        "There'sno information regarding the kind of differences in between the branches of  Rifa'iyya. Thus, it could be said that the names of the branches coming from the person who represented the tariqah or helped it spread in specific areas and there's no distinction between them regarding basis of sulooq. Thus, it's seen that the practice in Sayyadiyya, which is the main branch or the most spreaded branch of  Rifa'iyya from the first periods, isn't much different than the main tariqah which is in Ummabidah(Tahralı, Ahmad ar- Rifa'i, p.347)\n"
        "\n"
        "1. Haririyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Hassan Ali al-Hariri(d. 620/1223) who was the grand son by the daughter of Ahmad ar-Rifa'i(Haririzadah, l, vr. 288b-293a; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245). Hariri  is known as the first shaikh who started   Rifa'iyya in syria. Some of the writers mixed the information about them because of the similarity of their names with Abu Mohammad Ali  al-Hariri bin abu'l-Hassan(d. 645/1247), who was one of his mureeds.(tahralı, Ahmad ar- Rifa'i, p. 349-350).\n"
        "\n"
        "2. Sayyadiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Izzaddeen Ahmad as-Sayyad(d. 670/1271) the other grandson by the daughter of Ahmad ar-Rifa'i(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 58b, 261b; Hussain Vassaf, l, 243). Being the most common branch of yje tariqah, it's spreaded in lraq, Syria, Egypt, Hidjaz and Yemen.\n"
        "\n"
        "3. lmadiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to lmaduddeen al-Aqbar who is recorded as one of the khalifas of Ahmad ar-Rifa'i.(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "4. Qayyaliyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by lsmael al-Majzoob al-Qayyal who was born in the village of Ummabidah.(Haririzadah, lll, vr. 93b-95a; Hussain Vassaf, l, 244-245). After the mongols entered lraq in 656(1258), Shaikh lsmael, left his homeland and went to  Allepo and continued his practice in there till he passed away. In some sources, the founder of Qayyaliyya and lsmael al-Qayyal bin Abrahan al-Balhi(d. around  900/1495)  are mixed one another. (Tahralı, Ahmad ar-Rifa'i p. 351).\n"
        "\n"
        "5. Jandaliyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Jandal bin Mohammad ar-Rifa'i(d. 675/1276), whose tomb is in Manin around ash-Shaam.(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60a-b; Ahmad bin Mohammad al-Vatari, p. 107; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245).\n"
        "\n"
        "6.  Diriniyya\n"
        "\n"
        "AKA Aziziyya. Related to AbdulAzeez bin Ahmad ad-Dirini(d. 694/1295), the egyptian khalifah of Abu'l-Fath al-Baltaci, who is the mureed of Abu'l-Fath al-Vasiti, who was of the khalifas that Ahmad ar-Rifa'i sent to Alexandria.(see DIRINI).\n"
        "\n"
        "7.  Ataiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Reşated to Mohammad Atiyyah ar-Rifa'i (Vll./Xlll. centuries) who was  inhumed around al-Quds.(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245).\n"
        "\n"
        "8.  Qatnaniyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Sayyed Hassan al-Qatnani(d. 747/1346). (Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b; lll, vr. 73b-74b; Hussain Vassaf,l 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "9.  Nooriyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Nooraddeen Habeebullaah al-Hadisi(Haririzadah, lll, vr. 212a; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "10. lzziyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Abu'l-Faiz Hussain al-lzzi al-Misri.(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 58b-59a; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245).\n"
        "\n"
        "11.  Jabartiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to lsmael bin Abraham al-Jabarti(d. 806/1403).(see JABARTl, lsmael b. Abraham)\n"
        "\n"
        "12.  Fanariyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Mollah Fanari (d. 834/1431), who was khalifah of Antochian shaikh Abdurrahmaan bin Mohammad al-Hanafi. (Kamal b. Ahmad Ahlati, vr. 17a-21b; Haririzadah, ll, vr. 59a; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245).\n"
        "\n"
        "13.  lsaviyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Mohammad bin lsa(d. 930/1524) in Maghreeb.( El² (lng), Vlll, 526).\n"
        "\n"
        "14.  Sharaniyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Abdulwahhab ash-Sharani(d. 973/1565). (see SHa'RANl, Abdulwahhab bin Ahmad)\n"
        "\n"
        "15.  Burhaniyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Burhanaddeen Abraham bin Umar bin Ali al-Alavi.(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 59b, Hussain Vassaf, l, 245). As it's recorded in Tibyan, two different silsilah reaches Burhanaddeen Abraham, one through Jamaluddeen Abdulhameed bin Abdurrahmaan al-Qulhi, and the other through Abu'l-Abbaas Ahmad bin Abraham al-Jabbas and Burhanaddeen Abraham is seen a the founder of two different branches.\n"
        "\n"
        "16.  Fadhliyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to the ldian soofy Jamaluddeen Mohammad bin Fadhlullaah al-lndi al-Burhanpoori(d. 1029/1620) who was from the offspring of Ahmad ar-Rifa'i (Haririzadah, lll, vr. 31b-35a; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "17.  Jamiliyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Jamaluddeen al-lraqi.(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "18.  Sabsabiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Sulaiman as-Sabsabi(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "19.  Mahmoodiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Mahmood az-Zanji (Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b)\n"
        "\n"
        "20.  Ajlaniyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Mohammad bin Ajlan al-Hussaini, who was naaqibulashraaf(head of the institution which keeps the record of sayyeeds and shareefs in Ottoman Empire). (Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b; Hussain Vassaf, l, 245)\n"
        "\n"
        "21.  Mahdoomiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Mahdoom-i Jehaaniyan(d. 785/1384). (Haririzadah, ll, vr. 60b)\n"
        "\n"
        "22.  Ulvaniyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Related to Ahmad al-Ulvan(Hussain Vassaf, l, 246)\n"
        "\n"
        "23.  Ma'roofiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "This branch which is recorded by Hussain Vassaf as Ma'roofiyya relating it to shaikh Ma'roofi(Safina, l, 246) has to be the same branch which is called Maarifiyya which is related to shaikh Mahmad Maarifi(d. 1279/1863). lt's known that there were takkas which belonged to this branch in lstanbul, Kartal, Kasımpasha, Toygartepe and Manisa city in XlX. century and at the beginning of XX. century. \n"
        "\n"
        "24.  Vasitiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Hussain Vassaf didn't give any information about this branch, but only the name of it(Safina, l, 245). lt could only be guessed that it was a branch which came from the khalifah Abu'l-Fath al-Vasiti(d. 632/1234-35) who was sent to egypt by Ahmad ar-Rifa'i. Thus Murtaza az-Zabidi, recorded a silsilah coming from Abu'l-Fath al-Vasiti to Zakariyya al-Ansari(p. 59)\n"
        "\n"
        "Other than these branches, also recorded that branches called Badhiyya, Malikiyya, Hulooliyya occured in Egypt(lA, Xll, 13-14), the usually known as a private tariqah, Badawiyya was also observed as a branch of  Rifa'iyya for  the silsilah of Shaikh al-Barri, who was one of the mursheeds of  the founder of  badawiyya, Ahmad al-Badawi's, was reaching Ahmad ar-Rifa'i(DlA, V, 318), Zaynalabideen al-Jazari, who was the shaikhu'sh-shuyookh of  Allepo, wore the coat of  Rifa'iyya along with several other tariqahs(Gazzi, ll, 145), Zayniyya, which was a branch of Suhrawardiyya, was also a branch of  Rifa'iyya for Abdurrahmaan Shirsi, the shaikh of Zaynudden al-Hafi who was the founder of Zayn.yya was given khilafah by  Rifa'iyya and also united Suhrawardiyya and  Rifa'iyya(Haririzadah, ll, vr. 59b-60a, 107b). Murtaza az-Zabidi recorded a silsilah reaching himself, through Sayyeed Abdurrahmaan bin Mustafa al-Ayderoos(d. 1192/1778). (p. 58-59)."
</string>

    <string name="rufai6text" >"RUFAİ TARİKATI SİLSİLESİ\n"
    "\n"
    "Hz. Muhammed (s.a.v.)\n"
    "\n"
    "Hz.Ali\n"
    "\n"
    "Hasan el-Basri\n"
    "\n"
    "Habib A’cemi\n"
    "\n"
    "Davud et-Tai\n"
    "\n"
    "Ma’ruf el- Kerhi\n"
    "\n"
    "Seriyü’s- Sekati\n"
    "\n"
    "Cüneyd-i Bağdadi\n"
    "\n"
    "Ebu Bekir Şibli\n"
    "\n"
    "Ali el-A’cemi\n"
    "\n"
    "Ebu Aliyi Ruzbari\n"
    "\n"
    "Ebu Ali Gulam bin Türkan\n"
    "\n"
    "Aliyyü’l-Kari el- Vasiti\n"
    "\n"
    "Tarikat sahibi , Seyyid Ahmed er-Rufai"

</string>


    <string name="melami1text" >"Malaamiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "The History of Malaamiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Beside some people saying that Malaamiyya is a tariqah, there are also people claiming that it's not a tariqah which has specific rules, but it's the common name of people who adopt staying away from every kind of show-off and worldly worries. The thought that malaamiyya is not a tariqah is because of its founder and the date it was founded are unknown. The first period of Malaamiyya is known by the name Malaamatiyya. Abu Saleh Hamdun bin Ahmad bin Ammaar al-Kassaar played a great role in spreading malaamiyya first time in Nishaaboor, at the beginning of the 3rd century. Even if there was malaamiyya before Hamdun Kassaar, it became a tariqah during his time.\n"
        "\n"
        "There is also deep influence of Wahdat-i Vujood view of Muhyiddeen ibnu'l-Arabi in Malaamiyya. Malaamies hide their ibadah and situations regarding closeness to Allah Subhana wa Taala from people except salah with jamaah which is impossible to hide. If they reveal these, they condemn themselves. They try to live hiding themselves inbetween society, dressing like ordinary people not to let people understand their real situation. They don't value looks and show-off. People around them think that they are faulty people and condemn them  because of their exxeggerating in their hiding their goodness and displaying only bad sides. Arrogance and showing-off are the things which they dislike the most. lt's a rule in Malaamiyya to be protected from these bad habbits. They don't have a specific dress code or takkas. Malaamies don't tell about their suffering to anyone.\n"
        "\n"
        "Because declaring a slave a need, is asking help from needy. Because of this, asking Allaah Subhana wa taala for their needs and following the path of the Prophet(saw), are the two basis of slavery(to  Allaah Subhana wa taala). They succour eachother. Hamdun Kassaar says: \"Mu'meen has to be a candle during night and a baton during day for his brother.\" regarding this subject.\n"
        "\n"
        "Malaamiyya had influenced the tariqahs which started during the end of 4th century and grew during 5th and 6th centuries as Mawlawiyya.\n"
        "\n"
        "The history of Malaamiyya is divided into three periods.\n"
        "\n"
        "1st Period:\n"
        "\n"
        "Malaamiyya of Kassaariyya. Malaamiyya which belongs to Hamdu Kassaar and is called Malaamatiyya. Occuredin Nishaaboor during the 3rd century(hijri).\n"
        "\n"
        "2nd Period:\n"
        "\n"
        "Malaamiyya of Bayramiyya. The 1st period malaamiyya lost its true health in time by batini groups entering malaamiyya. lt was replaced by Bayramiyya Malaamiyya which occured by Hadji Bayram Wali in the city of Bolu, Göynük, during 9th century(hijri). Maşamiyya was spreaded in Anatolia by Hadji Bayram Wali.\n"
        "\n"
        "3rd Period:\n"
        "\n"
        "Malaamiyya of Nooriyya. This branch which belongs to Sayyeed Mohammad Noor al-Arabi, occured in Üsküp during13th century(hijri).\n"
        "\n"
        "These informations are gathered from the web site called \"sevde\" which belongs to A. Arı."

</string>


    <string name="bedevi1text" >"Badawiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Ahmad Badawi and Badawiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Founded by Hadrat Ahmad Badawi. He was born in Morocco in 596/1200 and his forefathers come from Hadrat Ali (ra) by Hadrat Hussain(ra) and Hadrat Hasan (ra). His family immigrated Makkah upon a spiritual sign while he was seven years old.\n"
        "\n"
        "He prefered lonliness while he was little. He didn't want to talk to anyone while in this situation. He used to fulfill his demands by signs. \n"
        "\n"
        "After that, he was asked to settle down in Egypt upon a spiritual sign. He headed the road after completing his preparation. He stepped by Baghdaad. He visited the graves of Hadrat Ahmad ar-Rufai and Hadrat Abdulqadir Jilani. After living here for a year, he passed to Tanta(a city in Egypt). When he came close to Egypt, Hasan Saigh Ahnai left Egypt saying: \"The real owner of this place is coming. Staying here doesn't befit us anymore\".\n"
        "\n"
        "He was called \"badawi\", because of his wrapping his mouth and nose just like badawis. According to another narratiın, this nickname was given to him by his family because of he couldn't get used to city life.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Ahmad Badawi whose nazaar(llook) is sharp, adhered to Sayyeed Ahmed ar-Rufai by means of Shaikh Ali bin Naeem al*Baghdadi and also adhered to Abu'l Hasan ash-Shazali on the first hand. Hussain Vassaf wrote this person is qutb and ghavs. \n"
        "\n"
        "Ahmad Badawi who has lots of titles as sayyeed, shareef, badawi, qutb, abu'l fana, and who resisted against crusades has books called Avraad, Salaats and Vasaya.\n"
        "\n"
        "He has given some advices to one of his close mureeds, Abdu'l-al. Some of them are:\n"
        "\n"
        "Oh Abdu'l-al, show compassion to orphans, clothe the naked, feed the hungry, treat the ghuraba(poor) and the guests. Hopefully this way you'd be one of maqbool(accepted) slaves on the sight of Allah(Subhana wa Taala).\n"
        "\n"
        "Beware from the love of dunia(world). For it disrupts the good deeds just as salt sours honey.\n"
        "\n"
        "Increase iin the rememberance of Allah(Subhana wa Taala), don't you ever be amongst ghafeels(aware of Allah Subhana wa Taala). Know that two rakahs of salah which is performed during the night is much virtuous than thousand rakahs of salah which is performed during the day.\n"
        "\n"
        "There had also been conflicts between Ahmad Badawi and scholars of fiqh just like the previous ahl al-tasawoof.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Ahmad Badawi passed away in 675/1276. Abdu'l-al took over after him as khalifah.\n"
        "\n"
        "Shaikh Abu'l-Fath al-Vasidi is an important khalifah of his who wet to Alexandria and spreaded the tariqah in there upon the order of his shaikh.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Shaikh AbdulAzeez is another khalifah of his.\n"
        "\n"
        "Tariqah of Badawiyya was spreaded in ash-Shaam, Yamaan, Hedjaaz, Iraq and other places. Takkahs of badawiyya were also opened in Istanbool. Shaikh Nail Efendi dargah around Kocamustafa Pasha, Mustafa Efendi dargah in Galata, Eburrıza Mehmed Şemseddin Efendi dargah in Beyoğlu, Shaikh Seyyid Efendi dargah and Shaikh Ahmed Efendi dargah in Beykoz, Mustafa İzzet Efendi dargah in Üsküdar and Shaikh Hasib Efendi dargah in Topbaşı tabaklar district are among these."

</string>
    <string name="bedevi2text" >"Initiation of the Tariqah\n"
        "\n"
        "The initiation ceremony starts with the questions and answers between the shaikh and the mureed. The mureed candidate replies the \"what's your desire and wish?\" question as \"I'd like you to be my guide to the path of afifeen(people who knows Allah Subhana wa taala).\". After the shaikh says \"I am ordering you only good and l want you to regard yourself against bad thing.\", he also tells the candidate repeats these things and thinks about their meanings all the time: \"Allah is with me, Allah is looking at me, Allah is whitness upon me.\". After salah and dhikr, acceptance ceremony starts. During this time, shaikh holds the thumb of the mıreed inside his hand and recites the 10 to 18th verses of surah al-Fath.\n"
        "\n"
        "Along with the badawi cardigan(darwish's coat), the banner and the flag are red. One day, when  Abdu'l-al(ks) asked his shaikh regarding the attributes of the person who carries this flag, he was replied: Not lying, staying away from prostitution, turning away from haraam(things forbidden by islam), being chaste, fearing Allah Subhana wa Taala, submitting to al-Qur'an al-Kareem, sticking to dhikr, continuing upon tafaqqoor(thinking about the creation of Allah Subhana wa Taala's. The coif which badawi darwishes uses is two parted and red turban is wrapped around the down part of it which covers the head.\n"
        "\n"
        "According to Badawi(ks), the base of dhikr is dhikr by heart. Still, during dhikr of badawiyya history, jahree(outloud) dhikr was made sitting. Badawi darwishes keep going by hugging eacother when their thrilling increases during the ceremony. This is called \"Badawi ball\". "

</string>
    <string name="bedevi3text" >"BEDEVİ TARİKATI SİLSİLESİ\n"
    "\n"
    "Hz. Ali(r.a.)\n"
    "\n"
    "Hasan Basri Hazretleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Habib-i A’cemi Hazretleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Davud’u Tai Hazretleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Ma’rufu Kerhi Hazrerleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Seriyü’s-Sakati Hazretleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Cüneyd-i Bağdadi Hazretleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Şihabeddin et-Tebrizi Hazretleri\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Ebu Yusuf Muhammed el-Kasım\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Abdül Kuddüs\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Abu Tahir Abdürrezzak\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Ali bin Hasan\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Abdülmecid el-Mağribi\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Abdülhamid\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Zeynüddin Abdülcelil\n"
    "\n"
    "Şeyh Seyyid Hasan bin Ali\n"
    "\n"
    "Hz. Pir, Seyyid Ahmed el-Bedevi(k.s.)"

</string>


    <string name="vefai1text" >"Wafaaiyya\n"
        "The most important source about the life of the founder of the tariqah Abu'l-Wafaa al-Baohdadi(d. 501/1107), is the arabic manaqibnama(book in which the supernatural events of a shaikh are gathered) which is called tazkiraatu'l-muttaqeen and tabsiraatu'l-muqtadeen, written by Shahabuddeen Ahmad al-Vasiti.  The lineage of Abu'l-Wafa reaches to lmam Zainal Abidin, according to Menaqib-i Taaj'ul-aarifeen Sayyeed Abu'l-Wafaa which was summarized and translated intihar Turkish by this name, by the will of Sayyeed Walaayat who was also a shaikh of Zainiyya, beside his being a member of Wafaai tradition. While his father, Sayyeed Mohammad living in Zabala region in lraq, he ran away from a proceeding towards sayyeeds, to the Kusan region and took refuge from a kurdish tribe called Banee  Narjees. He married a kurdish girl, and Abu'l-Wafaa was born here in 417(1026). Abu'l-Wafaa continued his education in Bukhara which he started in Baghdaad. Later he returned Baghdaad, he accepted Abu Mohammad Abdullah bin Talha ash-Shanbaqi who was one of the greatest shaikhs of that era, as his shaikh. His shaikh entitled him Abu'l-Wafaa, because of his loyalty and wafaa(fidelity). Abu'l-Wafaa started irshaad after he compleeted his sulooq(way of tariqah) and took his icazah. He became of the most important shaikhs of his time and his mureeds from every part of the society increased. Even though the rumors that 17 sultans were amongst his mureeds and the Abbasite khalifah Qaeem Biamrillah who was hesitating his influence due to him being sayyeed called him to his palace and inspected him were accepted exaggerated, it's important in showing the power and reputation he gained ( January, TTK Belleteni LXX/257(2006), p. 125). Abu'l-Wafaa who was narrated the first person to hold the title \"Taaj-ul Aarifeen\", spent a longpart of his life in Iraq and passed away i there on Rabeeul-awwaal 20th 501(8th november 1107).\n"
        "\n"
        "After Abu'l-Wafaa passed away, the tariqah of wafaaiyya spreaded a large area in lraq and Syria by the hands of khalifas like Ali b. Hayti, Ali al-Qurdi, Mead al-Qurdi, Jakir al-Qurdi, Bogha b. Batu, Abdurrahmaan b. Doghanji, Mohammad Turkmani, Shaikh Turhan, Shaikh Tekin, Mohammad b. Belikısa, Matar al-Bedrani, Ahmad b. Baqli al-Yamani, after that started their activities in Anatolia. Three of the khalifas of Abu'l-Wafaa being called by the title \"Qurdi\", indicates the effective influence of the shaikh in between the qurdish tribes. lt's understood that the effects of Abu'l-Wafaa is not limited by the qurdish environments due to being of other khaifas carrying Turkish names. The information regarding the situation of wafaaiyya in lraq and Syria which are the central spreading area, and till when the effects of it continued in those places are less according to the informationregarding Anatolia. lt's possible to track the effects of the tariqah in the Anatolia area easier, due to Menaaqibu'l-Qudsiyya of Alwan Chalabi, History of Ashiqpashazadah, and some archive documents. But these informations also don't belong to Abu'l-Wafaa's era or right after it, and they are limited by the activities of Dada Garkin and his khalifas' who probably lived after approximately a hundred years later. Dada Garkin, who probably came to Anatolia running away from the Mpngolian invasion, settled in Marash-Albistan at first.\n"
        "\n"
        "Even though it's written in Menaaqibu'l Qudsiyya that he is called \"Garkin\" due to the mercy of Allah Subhaa wa Taala encompassed him(p. 9-13), it's obvious that it came from the name of Turkman tribe which he was a member of. Just as  most of his likes in medieval Anatolia, Dada Garkin was both a tribe leader and a spiritual leader. lt's recorded that hia real name was Nouman according to the sayyeed genealogy (sayyeednama) which were written later (January, ln the Medieval Anatolia p. 45-47). Dada Garkin who has a great partin wafaaiyya's spreading especially around the country sides of Anatolia, gained admiration of Sultan Alaadddeen Kaiqubaad, who was known with his intimacy towards Turkman darwishes, sultan visited him personnally and granted him 17 villages(Elvan Chalabi, p. 8-9).\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Dada Garkin is shown as the founder of wafaiyya's Garkiniyya branch in the 821(1418) dated silsilahnama which belongs to Chalabi Sultan Mahmad era. Dada Garkin, gained a great influence at the southeast Anatolia. There are zawiyas which are said that they belong to him in Göksun, Hısnımansur, Malatya and Mardin. With a few tombs which are said they belong to him in a few places, it's strongly possible that his real tomb is the one in Mardin Dada village. Lots of zawiyas which were  named after him during the Ottoman era, this zawiyas still being active in the XVth century, shows the influence of the tariqah in the country side. lt's also known that there's an Alawee  dargah of Dada Garkin today. Wafaaiyya was spreaded around Anatolia mostly by the khalifas of Dada Garkin.\n"
        "\n"
</string>


    <string name="sazeli1text" >"Shazaliyya was fouded by Abu Hasan Shazali. Abu Hasan Shazali, who was born in Tunusia, started to spread the tarikah of shazaliyya in Tunusia at first. He made pilgrimage many times, He passed away in Egypt during his last pilgrimage. Lately, he went on lots of journeys seeing many coutries. At the end, he settled in Alexandria. After staying in Alexandria for a while, he went to Egypt and thaught \"Ibn Atiyya and Shifaa\" in there. Members of this tariqah don't pay attention to special dressses. They don't dispise begging. They don't accept acting upon certain rules. Making a living themselves, doing dhikr and dua all the time, not submitting to people, depending on Allahj Subhana wa Taala, remembering Allah Subhana wa Taala every moment, following the sunnah are amongst their main principles. Tariqah spreaded out mostly in Tunusia, Algeria, North Africa and Egypt. It's known that Shazaliyya played very positive roles in the struggle  of independency of the North Africa societies. Whereupon th Sunusies began independency actions, Sultan Abdulhamid the 2nd brought Hasan Zafeer -who is one of the shazaliyya shaiks- to Istanbul against them."
</string>
    <string name="sazeli2text" >"Ahmad Dhiyaauddeen Gumushanawi, said that tariqah of shazaliyya  has 5 Basis, in his Jaami ul-usool book, in which he mentioned the usool of tariqah:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"1- Being upon ittiqa(piety), openly and secretly in every single deed,\n"
        "\n"
        "2- Following sunnah in both action and words,\n"
        "\n"
        "3- Staying away from people(not expecting anything from people) during felicity and calamity times,\n"
        "\n"
        "4- Surrendering to Allah Subhana wa Taala(looking for His consent) in every small or great matter,\n"
        "\n"
        "5- Returning to Allah Subhana wa Taala(refuging) during happy and sad times.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "The reality of taqwah(piety), occurs by honesty and fear of Allah Subhana wa TAala.\n"
        "\n"
        "The reality of sunnah occurs by good morals and protecting oneself from forbidden things.\n"
        "\n"
        "The reality of turning away from baatıl(falsehood) occurs by sabr(patience) and tawaqool(trusting Allah Subhana wa Taala).\n"
        "\n"
        "The reality of being consent with what comes from Allah Subhana wa taala occurs by confining and surrendering.\n"
        "\n"
        "The reality of returning to Allah Subhana wa Taala occurs by being grateful for the situation he is in and not turning away from Him.\"(p. 86)\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Tariqah of shazaliyya being \"Junaidi\" by silsilah, at the same time it's a tariqah foccusing on spiritual education. Thus shaikh Shazali used to advice his mureeds renunciation of mortal existence for the sake of Allah Subhana wa Taala, wouldn't desire riyazah, khalwah, ceremonies and dhikr khalakas much. He used to suggest the members of tariqah to fulfill the duties and the soul of tariqah in their lives.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Shazalies, -who differ from the tariqahs which educate the mureeds by riyazah and suffering-, used to dress very clean, wouldn't hold back from worldly blessings, used to believe that it's possible to reach tawheed(oneness of Allah Subhana wa Taala) by nawafeel(deeds other than fardh), dua, dhikr amongst their jobs and occupations. The basic of tariqah is facing towards taqdeer(the decision of Allah Subhana wa Taala) and tawaqool(depending on Allah Subhana wa Taala), without trusting tadbeer(precaution) and tawasool(resorting)  and observing Allah Subhana wa Taala in every task and occurance around us.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Shaikh Shazali, tried to carry out persoally himself and his khalafs(following shaikhs), the moral maturity which the taswoofi pieces like Ihyaa ulumideen of Ghazalli, Kut'ul Quloob of Abu Taleeb al-Maqqi, ar-Riayah li-Hukookillaah of Harith al-Muhaasebi taught.\n"




</string>
    <string name="sazeli3text" >"Ahmad Diyauddeen Gümüshhanawi, who has caliphate from many tariqahs, ezplained the place of shazaliyya in tariqahs like this:  \"O the traveller of the path of eternity! Know that well, every wali(friend of Allah Subhana wa Taala) has his own way of himmah(spiritual help) during his life and death. For example, imprinting haqiqah(reality) to the heart, swimming in the sea of tawheed(oneness of Allah Subhana wa Taala), reaching the secret of fana(dissapearing in the presence of Allah Subhana wa Taala) and istighraaq(loosing consciousness),  and continuing of these secrets in his saaleeks(followers) by a great himmah even after he passed away, is the speciality of Bahaauddeen shah-i Naqshebend(ks). A strong tasaroof(possession, providence) and helping in every aspect for the people who are asking is the speciality of Abdulqadir Jilani(ks).  The tasaroof and himmah of hadrat Abu'l Hasen ash-shazali(ks)'s in the strength of ilm and revelation , hadrat Ahmad ar-rifaai(ks)'s in futuwah(generosity) and extraordinary conditions , hadrat Ahmad al-Badawi(ks)'s in mercy and atiifah(unconditional love, being big-hearted) , hadrat Ahmad Dusuqi(ks)'s in generosity and grace , hadrat  shaikh-i aqbar Muhyiddeen ibn al-Arabi(ks)'s in visdom and maturity(of the soul), hadrat mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi(ks)'s in love and muhabbah, hadrat imam Shihabuddeen as-suhrawardi(ks)'s in grace and modesty , hadrat shaikh Hidr Yahya(ks)'s in riyazah(eating few) an tahassoor(longing) , hadrat Najmuddeen-i Qubraa(ks)'s in vajd and jazbah(loosing consciousness by the love of Allah Subhana wa Taala) , continued during their lives and after their passing away. As much as these characteristics seem private for each wali, every single characteristic is the evidence for a special maqaam(spiritual place), and tasaroof of the wali who reached that place. Every group, reaches happines by the divine states which they are treated. And graces happen according to the value and ability of the wali.(p. 49)\".\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "The same point is indicated in the Diyanah Islam Encyclopedia like this:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Mutasaweefs(people of tasawoof) defend that every single wali has a special aspect himself, because some of the walis took more than one share of the tajalli of al-Asma al-Husna. For example, at  imprinting haqiqah(reality) to the hearts,   Bahaauddeen shah-i Naqshebend(ks), at helping people in trouble Abdulqadir Jilani(ks), at being enlightened by divine tajallis hadrat  Abu'l Hasen ash-shazali(ks), at showing supernatural things  hadrat Ahmad ar-rifaai(ks), at compassion and mercy hadrat İbraheem ad-dasuki(ks), at marifah(knowing Allah Subhana wa Taala) hadrat ibn al-Arabi(ks), at modesty hadrat Suhrawardi(ks), at jazbah ad istighraaq Najmuddeen-i Qubra(ks), at love and muhabbah Mawkana(ks) made a difference. Likewise, every single one of Hulefa-i rashideen has a different attribute from others, Truthfulness hadrat Abu Baqr's justice hadrat Umar's, hayaa(shyness9 HADRAT Uthman's, generosity hadrat Ali's (ridvanullahu teala anhum) attribute. The same situation goes with the prophets as well. Hadrat Adam is \"Safiyyullaah\" Noah \"Najeeyullah\", hadrat Ibraheem \"Haleelullah\", hadrat Moosa \"Qaleemullaah\", hadrat Isaa \"Roohullaah\", hadrat Mohammad \"Habeebullah\". (alaihimussalaam). (v.1, p.7)"





</string>
    <string name="sazeli4text" >"Dasuqiyya which is a branch of shazaliyya was spreaded out in Egypt and Sudan mostly. İbrahim bin Abdulazeez Dasuqi, the pir(master, leader) of tariqah of dasuqiyya which is known as burhaniyya and burhamiyya. Jahree(outloud) dhikr, being devoted to ibadah, loyalty to the rules of shariah and tariqah, imitating the akhlaq(morals) of awliyaa, opposing humanly desires, killing the nafs(ego) are the basics of dasuqiyya. The members  of the tariqah who usually wear green outfits, frequently repeat the dhikr of  \"yaa Daaim\" during their ceremonies.Even though İbrahim Dasuqi didn't allow samah(whirling while making dhikr), his khalifas made samah and mawleed ceremonies basics of dasuqiyya. Today, the sharnubiyya and shahaawiyya branches of dasuqiyya are active in Egypt. today dasuqiyya is common in Syria and Egypt.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Shazaliyya is one of the most common tariqahs in the world by its over 100 branches. Most poppular of these branches are:\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "wafaaiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Mohammad Wafaa b. Mohammad al-Maghrebi, 765/1364\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Yaafeiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Abdullahb. As'ad al-Yaafei 768/1367\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Jazooliyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Mohammad b. Sulaiman al-Jazooli 870/1465\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Aroosiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Abu'l Abbaas Ahmad b. Mohammad b. Aroos al-Hawaari 868/1463\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Zarrookiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Ahmad az-Zarrok 899/1493\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Maymooniyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Ali b. Maymoon al-İdrisi 917/1511\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Raashidiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Ahmad b. Yousuf ar-Raashidi 927/1521\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "İsawiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Mohammad b. İsa al-Maknasi al-Maghrebi 930/1524\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Baqqiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Umar b. Sayyeed Ahmad al-Baqqi at-Tunusi 960/1552\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Baqriyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Abu'l Maqaarim al-Baqri 994/1586\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Naasiriyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Mohammad b. Mohammad b. Ahmad b. Naasir ad-Dari 1085/1674\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Khidriyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Abdulazeez ad-Dabbagh 1132/1720\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Bayyoomiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Ali Nooraddeen b. Hijazi al-Bayyoomi 1183/1769\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Darqawiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Abu Haamed Mawlaay al-Arabi b. Ahmad ad-Darqawi 1239/1823\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Madaniyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Mohammad Hassan b. Hamzah Zaafer al-Madani 1263/1847\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Yashrutiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Sayyeed Ali Nooraddeen b. Yashruti at-Tunusi 1316/1899\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Alawiyya:\n"
        "\n"
        "Founder is Ahmad al-Alawi 1934\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Most of the branches of shazaliyya not continuing today or continuing in a branch of its.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Sources:\n"
        "\n"
        "Ahmad Diyaauddeen Gumushhanawi, Jaamiu'l-usool), Hasan Kamil Yılmaz, Anahatlarıyla Tasavvuf ve tarikatler, Mustafa Kara Tasavvuf ve Tarikatler Tarihi, İrfan Gündüz, Gümüşhanevi Ahmed Ziyauddin: Hayatı, eserleri, Tarikat anlayışı ve Halidiyye Tarikatı, Raşid Küçük, \"Abadile\" "

</string>


    <string name="mevlevi1text" >Mawlawiyya
        "\n"
        "Mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi and mawlawiyya\n"
        "\n"
        "Mawlawiyya is the name of the tariqah which is founded in the name of Mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi, by his son Sultan Valad. Mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi(1207-1274)  used to arrange special meetings which his friends attended, give tasawoofi and religious speaches, reads poems, and do sama' while doing dhikr. These meetings, which became ceremony in time, was adhered to specific principles of views and thoughts. Dhikr and ceremonies in which ney(reed flute), qudm(a small double drum) and such musical instruments are played, had been started to do well-coordinated and carefully.\n"
        "\n"
        "The number of attenders of these meetings which were spreaded to a large area in no time and attacted the interest of the society and the literates of the era, increased. There were attenders, and people wanted to attend from Iran, Arabia, Anatolia and lots of places from the world, there were people who harbored a deep love and respect towards Mawlana. In time, these special meetings were restricted, attached to specific rules and regular ceremonies.\n"
        "\n"
        "After Mawlana passed away, his son, Sultan Valad, brought these meetings which his father organised and the sama', dhikr and such ceremonies which are done in them upto a tariqah attribute by following his father's footsteps. He set some permanent rules which are common inbetween mawlawies to attend the ceremonies, tı be present at the meetings and to get in sama' and dhikr majlis(gathering). He made these official in time. He enlarged Mawlana's place(which is called \"takka\" later). At the beginning these gatherings were only in Konya(a city in Turkey). Fter people who adopted Mawlana's opinions and thoughts increased, opening of takkas and mawlawihanas in other cities were allowed by the takka of Konya which was the cetral takka. In time, Mawlawihanas, takkas were opened  in neighbour islam countries, just like in Anatolia. Mawlawiyya became one of the most common ones in sunni tariqahs. Mawlawihana of Konia, the turbah(tomb) which is called Kubba-i Khadra(or khadrat) (green kubba) , was adopted as the center and sacred place of the tariqah, and it was respected and loved."



</string>
    <string name="mevlevi2text" >"Basis\n"
        "\n"
        "The basic principles of Mawlawiyya are usually 12 branches:\n"
        "\n"
        "1. Serving humanity\n"
        "2. Setting an example of good mannors for others always\n"
        "3. Reading Masnawi and being mutasaweef(sufi)\n"
        "4. Using the intelligence well and having hikmah\n"
        "5. Being pious\n"
        "6. Keeping his inside(heart) clean all the time\n"
        "7. Accepting Mawlana as Pir(head of the tariqah)\n"
        "8. Not leaving the path of Mawlana\n"
        "9. Being committed to Mawlana, after Hadrat Mohammad (SAllallahu alaihi wa sallam), being attached to him spiritually\n"
        "10. Getting ilm, having knowledge\n"
        "11. Being modest, patient, genial and kind\n"
        "12. Being clean both phisically and spiritually"
        "\n"
        "These are the unchangable rules of Mawlawiyya. Everyone who joins the tariqah of Mawlawi, who undergoes a period of suffering has to obey these."
</string>


    <string name="mevlevi3text" >"Mawlana Tomb\n"
        "\n"
        "The tomb of Mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi's in Konya.\n"
        "It was built by Alamaddeen Qaisar and Muiniddeen Parwana and his wife Gurju Khatoon after Mawlana Jalaladdeen Rumi passed away(1274). The architect of it is Badraddeen Tabrizi. It's in the shape of kulliya by the masjjed, sama'hana, maidan-i shareef(square), matbah(kind of kitchen of the dargah), darwish cells(rooms), fountain, shab-i arooz pool and chalabi circle. Among the buildings which forms the kulliya, main tomb building belong to Saljuklu period grooved body and cone and the enterance corridor, chalabi graves, post dome belong to Karamanoghlu period, the masjeed, sama'hana, tombs, darwish  cells, kitchen and the fountain belong to Ottoman period. Today, the shape of the tomb is, three side arch and one side closed area on a square based floor. 16 segmented cone covers the top of this area. On top of the cone, there's a high flag, which has crescent with a Mawlawi specie in it. The cone is covered with turquoise tiles. The cone is called greendome. Under the greendome, there are marble chestswhich are covered with pushida(fancy fabric) which belong to Mawlana and his son Sultan Walad. There's also a balming part of the tomb, it's known that the door of this part which is placed on the front, under the silver sill has built in XVIII th century. The embalmed body of Mawlana is preserved in this part which is supposedşy covered by cross vault. "


</string>


    <string name="mevlevi4text" >"Jami Mawlawi Ceremony"\n" Theres also a ceremony in Mawlawiyya which is called jami Mawlawi. Other than grandsires, muheebs(people who like sufies) who join the tariqah also attend this ceremony which is mostly done during nights and has a conversation attribute. Baseman grand leads this ceremony. The red hide of the shaikh is laid next by the door. Then the others are alined in a row. 18 candlesticks are placeed in two rows whic have 9 candlesticks. After isha prayer is performed, the ceremony begins with the call of baseman grand. Reed flutes are blowned and the sama' ceremony begins. The Mawlawi takkas which used to be an art and education place at the begginning, became distant from this attribute by time. Their practise is ended by the law which foresees the closing of takkas and zawiyas.\\n\""




</string>


    <string name="kadiri1text" >"Firstly the shaikh and the mureed makes ghusl(whole body wudu). Then, mureed(the person who is willing to be a member of the tariqah)  gets all the other thoughts out of his heart and directs his love and will towards Allah Subhana wa Taala. He sees Rasoolullah Sallallahu Taala alaihi wa sallam as his waseelah(intercessor) to Allah Subhana wa Taala. And he puts his hands between the shaik's hands. Then the shaikh prays like this, after basmalah, hamdalah and salaat:\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\"O Allah! Surely l declare that l adopt this person only in Your path, by witnessing Your angels, pruphets and awleyaa(friends).  Accept him and my adopting. Be for him, don't be against him, grant him steadfastness and hold his hands.\"\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Then says to the mureed:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"O my son, from now on, do not sin, neither minor, or major. Do good deeds upon the Book of Allah Subhana wa Taala and the Shariah of Rasoolullah Sallallahu Taala alaihi wa sallam.  I accapted you to the path of Haqq, to unite the shariah and haqiqah(reality).\"\n"
        "\n"
        "After mureed saying that he accepted this, shaikh makes a proper dua and  the ceremony ends.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "After this, mureed keeps himself busy with his daily dhikr of hamdalah(praising AllahSubhana wa Taala), salaat(dua for prophet), dua, tawheed, and lafza al-Jalaal.  Riyaazat (austerity regarding food) is important.  The people who are accepted to this tariqah, stays in khalwat(worshipping in a place in which there's noone and nothing) as Abdulqaadir Jilani suggestted and the way he described.\n"
</string>
    <string name="kadiri2text" >"He declared the basics of qadiriyya in his will to his son as:\n"
        "\n"
        "Our path depends on\n"
        "\n"
        "The Book(Qur'an) and the sunnah(way of Rasulullah Sallallahu Taala alaihi wa sallam)\n"
        "\n"
        "Salvation of the heart\n"
        "\n"
        "Generosity\n"
        "\n"
        "Spreading the goodness\n"
        "\n"
        "Getting rid of the  hardship\n"
        "\n"
        "Baring the opression\n"
        "\n"
        "Overlooking the faults of our brothers in islam\n"
        "       In tariqah, dhikr(rememberance of Allah Subhana wa Taala) would be jahree(outloud).\n"
        "\n"
        "       Mureed wears a crown after one year.\n"
        "  \n"
        "\n"
        "       He should surrender himself fully to Allah Subhana wa Taala\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       His words and his deeds has to fit\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       He has to be upon ikhlaas(sincerity)\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Every situation and action including revelations coming to the heart has to be in according with the book and the sunnah\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       He has to follow shariah(the orders of Allah Subhana wa Taala) in zaheer(apparently).\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "        Abdulqaadir Jilani, who describes tasawoof as leaving gossip, places it onto eight habits which every single one of them is based on a single prophet. These are:\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Being geerous,\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Consentig Allah Subhana wa Taala and His will,\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Being patient,\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Talking using sign language,\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Knowing that the real homesickness starts with staying away from Allah Subhana wa Taala\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Dressing modestly\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Travelling to worship Allah Subhana wa Taala\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "       Knowing his faqr(poorness) before Allah Subhana wa Taala"
</string>
    <string name="kadiri3text" >"KADİRİ SİLSİLESİ\n"
    "1- Hz. Muhammed Mustafa(s.a.v.)\n"
    "\n"
    "2- Hz.Ali(r.a)\n"
    "\n"
    "3- Hasan Basri(K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "4- Habib A’cemi(K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "5- Davud et-Tai (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "6- Ma’ruf el-Kerhi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "7- Seriyyü’s-Sekati (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "8- Cüneyd-i Bağdadi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "9- Ebu Bekir Şibli (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "10- İzzeddin Abdülaziz bin Haris et-Temimi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "11- Abdülvahid bin Abdulaziz et-Temimi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "12- Ebu’l-Ferec Abdurrahman et-Tarsusi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "13- Muhammed bin Yusuf el-Kureşi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "14- Ebu Sa’d el-Muharremi (K.S.)\n"
    "\n"
    "15- Abdulkadir Geylani (K.S.)"

</string>
    <string name="kadiri4text" >"Abdulqaadir gilani and qadiriyya\n"
        "\n"
        "The founder of the tariqah(cult) is shaikh Abdulqaadir gilani. He (470 or 471/1078) was born in Gilan which is in Iran lands. His full name is  Muhyiddeen Abu Mohammad Abdulqaadir bin abi Saleh Moosa az-Zaheed al-gilani. His father's name is Abdullah and his mother's name is Fatimah. His lineage reaches hadrat sayyiduna Hasan(ra) from his father's side, and hadrat sayyiduna Husayn(ra) from his mother's side. So he's both sayyeed and shareef.\n"
        "\n"
        "Gilani, who lost his father in his little age, says:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"My father was as ascetic as he could to dunia(world). My mother followed him and accepted his behaviour. They were both saleeh, pious and compassionate people.May all the good deeds l have done, all the blessings l have be theirs.\"\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Abdulqaadir gilani tells:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"During my childhood, whenever l wanted to play with my friends, l used to here a voice saying \"You are not created for this\", and go to my mother scaring.\"\n"
        "\n"
        "According to his own statement, Abdulqaadir gilani married four women. He had 49 children -22 girls and 27 boys- from these marriages.\n"
        "\n"
        "After he completed his study(ilm) and his sulook( way of tasawoof), he started preaching at his shaik's madrassah(school of ilm). Yusoof al-Hamadaani couraged him for this.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Abdulqaadir gilani used to start his speech saying \"Al hamdu lillaahi Rabbil aalameen\", pause for a while, again say \"al hamdu liilaah\" and pause, then again after saying \"al hamdu lillaah\" make a long dua(prayer), and then start preaching.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Gilani used to preach on friday, tuesday and sundays. Lots of aaleem(scholars) and shaiks used to attend his sohbah(preaching). It's said he preached for 40 years.\n"
        "\n"
        "One day, during his speech, he declared his being the sultan of awleyaa(friends of Allah Subhana wa Taala), saying \"the necks of all the awleyaa is under my foot\", All the people in there accepted saying \" on top of our heads ( an expression meaning certainly accepted) \", For example, at that moment, Abdulqaadir as-Suhravardee said \" on top of my head, on top of my head, on top of my head \"while he was bending as his head was falling down on the ground.\n"
        "\n"
        "According to the sayings, not only the people in there, but also the people far away felt this spiritual incident. The awleyaa of Allah Subhana wa Taala in the places like Harran, Shaam, Tilemsam and Sinjaar heard this announcement and declared their acceptance. Hadrat Ahmad ar- Rifaai also replied \" on my neck\" while he was sitting in his takkah, and when he was asked the reason of those words, he told the announcement of Abdulqaadir gilani. Abu Madyan whom was in Maghreeb with his mureeds(sufies) at that time, also said \" O Allah, l make You and Your angels my witness, that l heard and l obeyed\".\n"

</string>
    <string name="kadiri5text" >"TITLES\n"
        "\n"
        "Abdulqaadir gilani is the one who has the most titles amongst awliyaa. Beside Ghaws al-Aazam, he has a lot of titles like Muhyiddeen ( the one who enlivens, revives the religion), al-Badhu'l Ashhab (white hawk), Badhullah(hawk of Allah), Qutb ul-Aqtaab(qutb of the qutbs), Ghaws us-saqalain(ghaws of men and jinn), Badal ul-abdaal, Asad ur-rijaal(lion of men), Shaikh ul-ins wal-jann( shaikh of men and jinn),Alaamat uz-zamaan(sign of time).\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "BOOKS\n"
        "\n"
        "He left a lot of precious books like\n"
        "\n"
        "Ghunyatu't Talebeen\n"
        "\n"
        "al-Fuyudhaatu'r-Rabbaniyya\n"
        "\n"
        ".futooh ul-ghaib\n"
        "\n"
        "al-Fathu'r-Rabbaai\n"
        "\n"
        "Jilaalu'l-Khatr\n"
        "\n"
        "Maqtoobat\n"
        "\n"
        "Sirru'l-asraar and Mazhaaru'l anwaar\n"
        "\n"
        "as-siraaju'l wahhaaj.\n"
        "\n"
        "SOME OF HIS QUOTES\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "-The person who realizes that everything is coming from Allah Subhana wa Taala, would be successful at doing khair(good things). Also would be safe from arrogance, because he could get rid of his nafs(self).\n"
        "\n"
        "-Good mannors is that the troubles of people wouldn't effect you.\n"
        "\n"
        "-People are barrier for you in both seeing your nafs(own self) and your Rabb. As long as you keep seeing people, you can't see your nafs. As long as you keep seeing your nafs, you live veiled from your Rabb.\n"
        "\n"
        "-Fear not, calamities don't come to destroy people, they come to experience and try.\n"
        "\n"
        "-Allah Subhana wa Taala's not accepting every single dua(prayer) coming from His slave, is because of His compassion. So that the slave wouldn't fall into a trap by seeing all his duas are accepted.\n"
        "\n"
        "-The real ihsaan(beneficence), belongs to the one who accepts the goodness from you, doesn't belong to you.\n"
        "\n"
        "-The most sever of the punishments is, looking for what is not written for you.\n"

</string>

    <string name="naksi1text" >"The school of naqshabandi education is a spiritual education system which Hadrat Haja Mohammad Bahauddeen Naqshabandi (who passed away in 791(hijri calendar), 1389(gregorian calendar) ) determined the basic usool. It's remembered as \"naqshabandiyya\" related to his name.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "This path and usool of education didn't start with Hadrat Shah-e Naqshaband. He took the usool, adab and faiz of this path from previous seniors. The usool and adab of this education path reaches Hadrat Abu Baqr Siddiq(r.a.) and Hadrat Rasoolullah(saw) from him by silsilah. Hadrat Rasoolullah(saw) is the head and center of this education. The main characteristic of this education path is secretly-made dhikr(dhikr by heart) and divine love. This way of dhikr and education was called by the names of different mursheeds who came during historical times.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "After Hadrat Abu Baqr siddiq(ra), this path was called \"siddiqiyya\". This name went on till Hadrat Bayazeed-e Bestami(ks). . Then it was called  \"Tayfuriyya\". Tayfur is the other name of Bayazeed-e Bestami(ks). This name went on till Hadrat Haja AbdulKhaliq Gujdawani(k.s). Then it was called \"Hajaganiyya\". It went on till Hadrat Shah-e Naqshaband.  After Hadrat Shah-e Naqshaband it was called  \"naqshabandiyya\". This path was spreaded out and became famous in the whole islamic world.  The names of other branches got forgotten in time. After Mawlana Khalid Baghdadi, this path was also called by the name \"naqshabandi khalidiyya\". Today the common branch in our Anatolia is the khalidiyya branch. Today, this path is called the famous name \"naqshabandiyya\" related to Hadrat Shah-e Naqshaband.\n"
        "\n"
        "Naqshaband is a word which is the combination of \"naqsh\" and \"band\" words. It's an adjective rather than a noun, but it's known as a noun.\n"
        "\n"
        "Naqsh means imprinting something to somewhere, to imprint as if it's never gonna be rubbed off, to grave like a seal.\n"
        "\n"
        "Band, is a Persian name, which is used both as a noun and an adjective in our language(Turkish). As a noun, it means tie, handcuff, dam, barrage, arch. As an adjective it means tied tightly, to tie tightly, tied strongly.\n"
        "\n"
        "The people of secret dhikr are called naqshabandi, because they imprint the dhikr of Allah Subhana wa Taala in a way that it's never gonna be rubbed off and because they would never detach from it(dhikr). \n"
        "\n"
        "Tarikah means path and usool. Tariqah  is not a madhab(sect) or deen(religion), rather it's a qay of understanding and living the deen. It's founded in order to educate people. Tariqahs are known by different names according to the usool(method) and dhikr which they prefer. The source of tasawoof isn't the philosophy of the east or the false religions of west, but rather it's Qur'an and sunnah.\n"
        "\n"
        "The whole ways of education are called \"tasawoof\" in short. The education of naqshabandiyya is founded upon secret dhikr(without moving the tounge, by heart). It has reached today by being developed by the great walies who adopted this usool. These usool and adab(proprieties) are taken from the verses of Qur'an itself, the sunnah of our prophet Hadrat Mohammad (Sallallahu Taala alaihi wa sallam) and the aspects of His honorable companions(Ridvanullahi taala anhum). It's connected to Qur'an and sunnah in every aspect. The usool and adab of this path are either defined clearly in Qur'an and sunnah, or accepted by the ways of isharah(signing), dalalah(pointing) or silence.. So there's nothing which doesn't belong to the spirit of islam.\n"
        "\n"
        "Just as the way Fakihoon(jurisprudents) have the authority of doing ijtihaad(jurisprudence), the kameel mursheeds have the authority of ijtihaad  in morals and education fields and the authority of defining new usool.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "This education system is not a new religion, rather it's a school of exercise and application of the moral lessons of the religion. Its target is to deliver people to good morals and the concent of Allah Subhana wa Taala. Its method is to tie the hearts to Almighty Allah by muhabbah(love). Its basic usool is to improve the bad attributes of the nafs(self ego) by secret dhikr, dhikr halaqas, muhabbah, causeries, rabita(connecting with the mursheed as if he's by the mureed's side), tawajjooh(turning to the mursheed), tasarroofpossession,), services and decency.\n"
        "\n"
        "The deeds and manners which our religion taught us could be summed in two sections:\n"
        "\n"
        "1- Apparent aspects:  Includes all the deeds which our body does with the outer organs. Eating, drinking, purity, shopping, law of family are included in this section. We have to learn the divine commands about the deed which w eare doing.\n"
        "\n"
        "2- Internal aspects: It's the awakening of the heart from heedlessness and enlivening of it by dhikr, purification of the nafs from the spiritual illnesses, ascension of the soul to the presence of Allah Subhana wa taala and this way man reachingthe divine noor(light), ilm, şove, decency and good morals, \n"
        "\n"
        "The internally and externally educated person's greatest achievement is good slavery. This aspect is called ihsaan grade in short.  We defined ihsaan hereinabove. This path is open to anyone. The whole people are invited to these decency and blessings.\n"
        "\n"
        "The person who preserves the internal and apparent decency obtains the ihsaan grade. The person who obtains this grade is loved and accepted by Almighty Allah. His heart is filled by the divine love, awe, hayaa(bashfulness) and hashyah(awe)."
</string>
    <string name="naksi2text" >"Hadrat Ahmad al-Khaznawi tells the basis of the tariqah of naqshabandiyya like this: \"Know that, the noble and sacred tariqah of naqshabandiyya is the path of the sahabah of the prophet(saw), is according to that basis. They neither added anything to it or removed anything from it. Their tariqah is,internally and externally not leaving the sunnah of the prophet(saw) or the rules of the religion and guarding themselves from bid'ah(innovations) and ruhsah(permits) in every act, tradition, deed and treatment by being with the spiritual presence of Allahu Taala.\" Ahmad al-Khaznawi, Maktoobat, 25\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Sayyeed Mohammad Rasheed said that about the purpose of the tariqah:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"The purpose of the tariqah is to improve your own nafs and study muhabbatullah to gain ikhlaas(sincerity). The fundamental of this is muhabbah and making effort.\" A. Selahaddin Kınacı, Gül Nesil 63 years, 104\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Sayyeed Mohammad Rasheed :\n"
        "\n"
        "Naqshabandiyya is a true and priceless tariqah. Benefitting  from this and reaching the goal  is possible only by avoiding the things which don't fit the tariqah, following the path of the tarqah and targetting to reach Allah Subhana wa Taala. If the rules are followed, one cannot benefit anything else like the benefit of it. This is the most shortcut and safe path which leads the people to Allah Subhana wa Taala. But, to become a true naqshabandi, one has to act upon thr adab(proprieties),  conditions and instructions of the tariqah, do the rabita(connection to the soul of the shaikh) carefully.\n"
        "\n"
        "This is such a great tariqah that, changes get started even before one adopts it. The muhabbah of Allah Subhana wa taala starts to fill in, he turns away from the world. But after being a member of the tariqah, these aspects start getting stronger.The love of dunia dies, it's seen that  the old stinginess, hatred, grudge and enmity aspects are gone, the old habbits are abandoned.He sees that all the friends are changed. His nature changes, he becomes sweet-tempered and patient. The talks about Allah Subhana wa taala becomes sweeter than anything, deeds feel nice. He turns his face towards Allah Subhana wa Taala in a very short time after he became naqshabandi. Some even mixes the awliyaa of Allah Subhana wa Taala  as soon as he make tawbah(repent) holding the hand of the shaikh before lissening the adab instruction. \n"
        "\n"
        "When the memners of naqshabandiyya look at the others, they see them taking and doing anything comes their way without thinking if it is halal or haram and them being unaware of tariqah. But he starts noticing these when he becomes a member.  He looks for the friendship of Allah Subhana wa Taala by sticking to the \"O my Rabb! I regret all the sins l've mad, l'm regretful\" promise he made his Rabb. The friendship of Allah Subhana wa taala protects man from the shar(evil) of shayateen(devil), for the member of tariqah is constantly busy with dhikr, devil cannot come close to him.\"  A. Sekahaddin Kınacı, Gül Nesil year 63, 96-97\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "The methods of all haqq(true) tariqahs leads to the path of shaba-i kiraam(companions). In the tariqah of naqshabandiyya, there is progress and reaching great degrees in a short time. For example a saleeq(member) of naqshabandiyya reaches the spiritual degrees which the members of other tariqahs reach at the end of the way just at the beginning. Hadrat Imam Rabbani says such about this situation:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"The path of sadat-i kiraam is the path of sahaba-i kiraam. The  himmah nazaar(eye, look of help) of these great people is truly way too great. The people who just start walking through this path  reached the spiritual degrees which the members of other tariqahs reach at the end of the way just at the beginning. The distinctive feature of them is  that they find  peace continuously. The nazaar of sadat-i kiraam is healing for the sick hearts. They are painted by the paint of sahaba-i kiraam. No matter what others say!... Because, subsequents cannot understand the hakikah(reality) of this.\"  İmam-i Rabbani, Maktoobat, 336th maktoob.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "İmam-i Rabbani spreaded out naqshabandiyya, even though he was a kameel murshid who has icazah from many tariqahs. ruled by the basis of the path of naqshabadiyya in the society he lived. He telled the reason of this by these words: \"The head of naqshabandiyya tariqah is our master Hadrat Abu Baqr(ra). He, is the most blessed person of the humanity after prophets. Because of this, the nobles of naqshabandiyya path said, \"Our affiliation is above all affiliations.\". For their affiliation is nothing but spiritual tranquility.The affiliation of Hadrat Abu Baqr (ra) is also above all affiliations. The most important attribute of naqshabandiyya tariqah is that the spiritual pleasures which would be gained by other tariqahs could be gained at the beginning in this path. Because of that, Hadrat Shah-i Naqshaband said: \"We put the end of tasawoof to the beginning of this path.\".  İmam-i Rabbani, Maktoobat, 221st maktoob.\n"
        "\n"
        "The tariqah of naqshabandiyya, doesn't harbor the hardship of the religion like the other tarbiyya dispositions, it's full of easiness. Nevertheless, it's very strict regarding bid'ahs(innovations). Given this, it's the hardest of tariqahs. Sadat-i naqshabandiyya also  carries out this hardship by their unique usool of tarbiyya just like every other disposition. \n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Sayyeed Sibghatullah Arwasi used to advice this to his mureeds regarding this subject:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"Our path doesn't include some burdens and hardships, Because of that it's easy. Naqshabandiyya doesn't accept bid'ahs, doesn't compromise Qur'an and sunnah. And because of that, it's the hardest of tariqahs. Aalim(people of knowledge) could get over this hardship by his knowledge, and the jaheel(people who don't have any knowledge) could get over it by trying to improve his nafs. \"  İbrahim Tozlu, Altın silsile, 356\n"
        "\n"
        "Because of sadat-i naqshabandiyya having extremely strich attitude against bid'ahs, while awliyaa of Allah Subhana wa Taala like Hadrat Imam-i Rabbani and Hadrat Sayyeed Abdulhakeem Bilvanisi saying: \"The path of naqshabandiyya is going to last till qiyamah(doomsday).\"  Imam-i Rabbani, Maktoobat, 251st maktoob, Ghaws-i Bilvanisi 42nd talk; correspondingly, it's known that many tariqahs which involved in bid'ahs would dissappear in time.\n"
        "\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Sayyeed Sibghatullah Arvwasi said regarding this subject:\n"
        "\n"
        "\"The future of innovations is bad and dark. No goodness could be expected out of these. People who defend such practices, say that they conduce towards goodness. But this isn't true. People who gain status, superiority in our path are accepted only if they stay out of bid'ahs. This is the characteristic of our path. There's no bid'ah in our path. One of  the reasons that some tariqahs getting reduced today is that they are involved in bid'ahs.  Today, the tariqah which stayed away from bid'ahs and didn't turn away from the right path(naqshabandiyya) could benefit people. Today it's very hard to get benefit from any other path of tasawoof. The greats of our path said :\" The most pure and common of tariqahs is naqshabandiyya and the most accepted of madhabs of fiqh is hanafiyya.\" regarding this subject. \". İbrahim Tozlu, Altın Silsile, 361"


</string>
    <string name="naksi3text" >"Nakşibendi Tarikatı Silsilesi\n"
        "\n"
        "Hz. Muhammed Mustafa (sav)\n"
        "Hz. Ebubekr Sıddık (ra)\n"
        "Selman-ı Farisi Hz. (ra)\n"
        "Ebu Muhammed Kasım Hz. (rah)\n"
        "Şeyh İmam Cafer-i Sadık Hz. (rah)\n"
        "Şeyh Bayezid-i Bistami Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Ebu Hasen Harakani Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Ebu Ali Farmedi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Hace Yusuf Hemedani Hz. (ks)i\n"
        "Şeyh Abdülhalık Gücdevani Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Hace Arif-i Rivegeri Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Hace Mahmud İnciri Fağnevi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Hace Ali Ramiteni Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Muhammed Baba Semmasi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Seyyid Emir Külal Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Şah-ı Nakşibend Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Alaeddin Attar Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Yakub-i Çerhi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Ubeydullah Ahrar Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Mevlana Muhammed Zahid Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Mevlana Derviş Muhammed Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Hace Muhammed Emkeneki Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Muhammed Baki Billah Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh İmam-ı Rabbani El-Müceddi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Muhammed Ma’sum Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Mevlana Muhammed Seyfeddin Faruki Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Seyyid Nur Muhammed Bedauni Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Mirza Mazhar Can-ı Canan Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Abdullah-ı Dıhlevi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Mevlana Halid-i Bağdadi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Seyyid Abdullah Hakkari Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Seyyid Taha Hakkari Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Gavs-ı Hizani Şeyh Seyyid Sıbgatullah Arvasi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Abdurrahman Tahi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Fethullah Verkanisi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Muhammed Diyaeddin Nurşini Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Ahmed Haznevi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Gavs-ı Kasrevi Şeyh Seyyid Abdulhakim Bilvanisi Hz. (ks)\n"
        "Şeyh Sultan Seyyid Muhammed Raşid Hz. (ks)"

</string>
    <string name="naksi4text" tools:ignore="TypographyDashes">"\n"
"1- Hush Dar Dam:\n"
        "\n"
        "Being ready in every single breath you take.. Means, protecting tranquility in every single breath one takes, not taking even a single breath being unaare of Allah Subhana wa Taala..  Meaning preserving peace in every single breath, not taking a single breath in being ghafeel(unaware) of Allah Subhana wa Taala.. Mawlana Sadatteen Kashghari defines this as: Never falling into unawareness and being at the presence(of Allah Subhana wa Taala) while passing from one breath to another. Hadrat Hodja Ubaidullah defines as :\n"
        "\n"
        "-- They have given weight to preserving the breath and observance of it in this path. It's necessary to take every single breath in and give it out by peace and knowledge.. They see those who can't preserve their breath as they lost their way.\n"
        "\n"
        "Shah-i Naqshaband:\n"
        "\n"
        "--Fundamental of progress in this pathis upon the breath. It's necessary to control the situation in every single breath, not to get distant from thinking the past and the future. One should preserve the space between two breaths during taking it in and giving it out such that none of them neither enter the body nor get out in the condition of unawareness..\n"
        "\n"
        "Ghaikh Najmadden-i Kubrah tells the secret of the breath in his famous risalah:\n"
        "\n"
        "--The dhath name of Allah Subhana wa Taala is nothing but the harf(letter) ha-he, the aleef and laam in front of it are preposition of description, in every single breath this harf and name circulates. Whether the owner notices or not. The thing in which that name doesn't circulate , doesn't deserve to live. In this case, the breathing of all the living creatures, is by that name for the knowing and the unknowing. The obligation of the traveler of marifah is to know this subtlety and hold the peace in every single breath by being with Allah Subhana wa Taala.\n"
        "\n"

"2- Nazaar Bar Qadam:\n"
        "\n"
        "This term means the eye is supposed to look at the feet.. Saaliq has to lock his eyes onto his feet, look towards the ground always and protect the eye from gazing at the place it wants in the city, at the desert, on the road, in every single place. In this, we read the hikmah(wisdom) of the heart -which flows to the place where the eye looks- being saved from being miserable and sticking to the inner world of itself."
        "\n"
"3-- Safar Dar Watan:\n"
        "\n"
        "This term meaning Journey at the homeland , indicates the mureed getting rid of the bad morals and humanly attributes, making a journey to his real homeland which is the land of good morals and angelic attributes. The material journeys to search a mursheed are also included in this meaning. In the path of Haajagaan travelling till finding his musheed and then staying at the service of the mursheed and completing the inner journey is of the main rules."
        "\n"
"4-- Khalwat Dar Anjuman:\n"
        "\n"
        "Meaning loneliness in the society.. Hadrat Hodja Bahauddeen Naqshaband was asked:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- What's the basis of your tariqah? He replied:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- Khalwat dar Anjuman, loniless in the society. Being with the people on the outside while being with Haqq Subhana wa Taala on the inside..\n"
        "\n"
        "And he said:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- The basis of our tariqah is confabulation. There's fame in staying away from the society, and calamity in fame. Khair(goodness) is in the society, society is in the confabulation.. It's appropriate to do the both and not to get stuck into one of them..\n"
        "\n"
        "Hodja Awliyaa-i Kabeer said:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- Loneliness in the society is this: Dhikr would cover the person so much, he would give himself into dhikr so muchthat he wouldn't here a thing even if he  enters the most crowded and uproarious place..\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Hodja Ubaidullah:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- If one gives himself into dhikr fully, he would reach such a degree that he sees all the yellings and quarrellings of the people as dhikr. And his own talking as well.."
        "\n"
"5-- Yaad-i Kard:\n"
        "\n"
        "Dhikr of the tounge along with the heart.\n"
        "\n"
        "Mawlana Saadeddin Kashghari:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- The usool of the taleem of dhikr is such, that while the shaikh is saying the kalimah of tawheed by heart, mureed would prepare his heart, holding his heart up against the heart of the shaikh, close his eyes, press his tounge against the roof of his mouth, squeeze his teeth and start making dhikr only by his heart.. He would be patient with holding his breath and say kalimah of tawheed three times in one breath.. Thus he would look for the taste of the dhikr in his heart..\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Hodja Ubaidullah:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- The purpose of dhikr, is the heart getting knowledge from Allah Subhana wa Taala. When this knowledge occurs, it means the dhikr has founded its place. If this knowledge doesn't occur in the confabulation of the ahl al-heart, it's necessary to continue the dhir. The easiest and the the most solid way of dhikr is by holding the breath under the belly, pressing lip to the lip and tounge to the roof of the mouth. The hakikah of the heart is being such center of the feeling and understanding that it heads every direction, always thinks the world and the worldly affairs and wanders around the world, the sky and all the places till the blink of eye, It's necessary to turn it back to the breast and tie it with dhikr by taking it away from all the ideas and makint it disgusted of them.Such that, by pulling the (laa) syllable of the kalimah of tawheed upwards, throwing the (ilaaha) word to the right side and hitting the (illallah) word down onto the heart by harshness and strength.. Such that, he has to feel the heat of the dhikr all over the body and melt in that heat.. At the laa ilaaha part of the kalimah of tawheed which is called nafy, mureed would dive into an absolute absence with his own body; at the ilallaah part which is called ispah, he would aasign the presence only to Allah Subhana wa Taala. Mureed would attach all the time he has got to this dhikr and no activity could keep him away from this dhikr just as the heart beat. Finally dhikr would become the indispensable attribute of the heart.\n"
        "\n"
        "The heart is in the shape of a triangular piece of flesh, which is below the left lobe and it's the whole center of the human reality. This piece of flesh is such a word that the whole reality is its meaning. Whole human reality is such a core that the whole universe is its detailed expression. Just as its own tree being as an extract inside of the seed of every fruit, the whole universe has been put inside the heart as a core. In short, heart is the copyprint of the whole beings as an extract and it's the collection point of the endless secrets.  The one who finds his way to the heart  reaches the goal, finding a way to it is possible by reaching the service of ahl al-heart. Then such a situation occurs to the mureed that he gets rid off the gossip of the things and events and he reaches the conversation of the soul and the heart the knowledge of Allah Subhana wa Taala. He also gets clear of everything but Allah Subhana wa Taala without any hardsip or struggle. Then the mureed understands the hikmah, the freedom of leaving the things and understands the hakikah of dhikr."
        "\n"
"6- Badh-i Qasht:\n"
        "\n"
        "Driving away any idea which is good or bad coming to the mind during dhikr.. It's obligatory for the heart to reach the belief of  O Allah! You are my intention, and your consent; nothing other than that!. As long as other interests take place in the heart, such belief couldn't occur and dhikr couldn't become pure. Although one couldn't reach this belief at the beginning, still it's necessary not to leave the dhikr but  to continue till this feeling is obtained.\n"
        "\n"
        "Mawlana Aliyyuddeen says:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- When l was ordered to do dhirk at the beginning l didn't adopt   O Allah! You are my intention, and your consent; nothing other than that! belief, l was ashamed of such a claim. For l wasn't true in this claim. It would be me telling a lie. I told my usthad about the situation. He said: one has to be steadfast in this till he makes it turn into reality even though he isn't true in this word. Later ı understood the hakikah of it.\n"
        "\n"
        "Fully truthfullness, is in this steadfastness and insistence which even makes the lie become truth."
        "\n"
"7- Nigah-i Dasht\n"
        "\n"
        "This is the muraqabah(keeping under control) of khawatir which means the strange feelings and thoughts coming to the heart suddenly and needed to be get rid of. So that not even a single strange thought shouldn't come to the mureed's mind although he remembers Allah Subhana wa Taala thousand times. Hadrat Mawlana Sadaddeen Kashghari said regarding this subject:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- Mureed has to protect himself from khawatir for an hour or two, if possible longer than that time.\n"
        "\n"
        "Mawlana Qasim who is of the superior khalifas of Hadrat Hodja Ubaidullah's said:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- Nigah-i dasht has to reach such high level that not even a single strange thing shouldn't come to the heart of the mureed. Such that the dreaming strength of the person has to dismiss itself.\n"
        "\n"
        "It's known by ahl al-hakikah that cutting the strength of dreaming up even for half an hour is an extremely hard end rarest job. It could only be the profit of some high walees."
        "\n"
"8- Yaad-i Dasht:\n"
        "\n"
        "The situation of being aware of Allah Subhana wa Taala by conscience and pleasure in every single moment and place.. Some defined this situation as peace without loosing himself. Again according to ahl al-hakikah this situation comes from Haqq's mirror of shuhood 's infestation of the mureed.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hodja Ubaidullah,sums the  yaad-kard, badh-gasht, nigah-dasht ve yaad-dasht as:\n"
        "\n"
        "Yaad-kard is nothing but pushing himself by dhikr and insistance by exaderration. Badh-gasht, is turning to Allah Subhana wa Taala and aiming Allah Subhana wa Taala every time he remembers His name. Nigah-dasht, protecting the situation of turning to Allah Subhana wa Taala without declaring by tounge. Yaad-dasht is nothing but getiing deep into the situation of nigah-dasht and using it with knowledge.."
        "\n"
"9- Vukoof-i zamaani:\n"
        "\n"
        "Shah-e naqshaband says on this matter:\n"
        "\n"
        "--Vukoof-i zamaani  is one of the biggest factors which concludes the mureed's whole efforts and makes him reach his goal. It means one knowing himself every second, and understand if he is in condition of shukr(gratitute) or apology.\n"
        "\n"
        "Yaqob Sharhi:\n"
        "\n"
        "-- Hadrat Bahaaddeen Naqshaband ordered us tawbah(repenting) in condition of qabd(having hard time), and shukr in condition of bast(reprieve). Paying attention to these two conditions and observing them is vukoof-i zamaani.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Hodja:\n"
        "\n"
        "--The mureed's profit building is built upon the time at the job of vukoof_i zamaani. Meaning, the statute of the condition of the mureed, depends on his preserving his time. Till he knows if every single breath he takes passes in peace or unawareness(of Allah Subhana wa taala)..\n"
        "\n"
        "According to the seniors of tasawoof, vukoof-i zamani is nothing but muraqabah(supervising) and muhasabah(accounting) of the nafs(self).\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Hodja:\n"
        "\n"
        "--Muhasabah is the calculation of every single hour upon the point of peace or unawareness. If there is a lack in the condition, then  it's necessary to start the deeds over by clinging on the usool of badh-i gasht."
        "\n"
"10- Vukoof-i Adadi:\n"
        "\n"
        "The work of paying attention to the number of dhikr and observing it… Hadrat Hodja Bahaadden-i Naqshaband, indicates that paying attention to th number of dhikr by heart and observing it gathers khawatir(thoughts other than Allah subhana wa taala) and erases it.\n"
        "\n"
        "Vukoof-i adadi isn't counting, but getting deep into the dhikr by heart within the framework of counting according the path of hajagan. It's necessary to do the dhikr of Allah 3,5,7 or 21 times at one breath and this measure of quantity ends with odd numbers..\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Hodja Alaaddeen Attar:\n"
        "\n"
        "--The case isn't much dhikr by quantity but by quality. Meaning much dhikr in peace and consciousness. No matter how much the quantity is, it means gainless tiredness as long as the production of it is pure. The production of dhikr occurs by the attributes which indicates the human body is combine with absence during the nafy(laa ilaha) part of kalimah tawheed and a transfiguration from the divine jazbah(rapture) is seen during the ispah(ilallah)  part of kalimah tawheed.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Shah-i Naqshaband:\n"
        "\n"
        "The attribute which is called vukoof-i adadi is the first degree of ilm( islamic knowledge) of ladun.\n"
        "\n"
        "The meaning of this has to be the authority and jazbah products which belongs to the mureeds at the beggining. \n"
        "\n"
        "Thus Hadrat Alaaddeen Attar said:\n"
        "\n"
        "--Such a condition and quality that the beginning of the intimacy(with Allah Subhana wa taala) and the ilm of ladun transfigurates by it. vukoof-i adadi being the beginning point of the ladun ilm is by its informing about the secret of its appearance in the world of Absolute One's. Just like  waheed's being the core of numbers in basis..\n"
        "\n"
        "Two verses:\n"
        "\n"
        "The appearance of the seen plurality is nothing but a show;\n"
        "The reality in the transfigurations is nothing but The One\n"
        "\n"
        "A stanza:\n"
        "\n"
        "Plurality is oneness as itself;\n"
        "Existence is in The One.\n"
        "Whatever you see as double, \n"
        "Know that it's one again.\n"
        "\n"
        "A stanza:\n"
        "\n"
        "According to ahl al-hakikah, all numbers are within one. For no matter how much the numbers increase, their reality is still one.\n"
        "\n"
        "vukoof-i adadi which is the first grade of ladun ilm is reaching such understanding.\n"
        "\n"
        "Ladun ilm is such a knowledge that would be known by ahl al-yaqeen(people who are intimate with Allah subhana wa taala) only and only by teaching of Allah Subhana wa taala, not by evidences or observations which are tied to intelligence.. Thus Qur'an praises Khidr by having the ladun ilm.The difference between the ilm of yaqeen and the ilm of ladun is that, whilst ilm of yaqeen is nothing but perception of the divine zaat and noor, ilm of ladun is percieving the meanings by the way of inspiration from Allah Subhana wa taala."
        "\n"
"11- Vukoof-i Qalbi\n"
        "\n"
        "Has two meanings: One of them is the person who does dhikr's knowing Allah every sigle moment.. This is a Yaad dasht kind of bussiness..Hadrat Hodja Ubaidullah says on this matter:\n"
        "\n"
        "--vukoof-i qalbi is a condition of heart on beig aware of Allah Subhana wa taala. Such that, there would be nothing but Allah Subhana wa taala in the heart..\n"
        "\n"
        "Again Hadrat Hodja Ubaidullah:\n"
        "\n"
        "--Being aware of the One who is being remembered by dhikr and assign the heart only to Him.. This awareness is called vision, access, revival and vukoof-i qalbi.\n"
        "\n"
        "Second meaning:\n"
        "\n"
        "The doer of dhikr heading towards the heart.. Towards the sharp ending piece of flesh with curvy sides which is metaphoricly called heart.. That piece of flesh is right under the left lobe and it's the point on which the whole attention would be gathered. The intention by vukoof-i qalbi is that piece of flesh's melting in the heat of dhikr by never being unaware of it. Hadrat Shah-i Naqshaband paid attention to these two points of vukoof-i qalbi.\n"
        "\n"
        "Just as turning towards qabah and opening hands to Allah Subhana wa taala whilst Allah Subhana wa taala is present everywhere, according to one vers, the path is founded by heading towards the soul's qabah(heart) and can't go without it. For the person is jailed in the prison of appearance of figures surrounding him and the prison of directions with regard to his bestial sol. But, again, the same person is on the outside of the aspects and directions by his self reality. From this perspective, the prisoner of aspects and directions has to search aspectlessness again within the aspect. And again from this perspective, the piece of flesh which is metaphoricly called heart, becomes  the sign of the reality of the soul and some kind of  assignment point of aspect. To find a way to haqiqah, it's necessary to head towards this metaphor point and find the key of ladun ilm in it.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hadrat Hodja Abdulkhaliq, has given glad news of dawah and being worthy of the state of irshaad to four people from his close ones when his passing away came close.\n"
        "\n"
        "Quotation from Rashahah.."
        "\n"
        

</string>

    <string name="Celvetiyye1" >"Tasavvufta ilk dönemlerde bir meşrep ve makam adı olan halvet* ve celvet*, daha sonra birer tarikat adı olarak kullanılmaya başlanmıştır. Bir Celvetî şeyhi olan İsmâil Hakkı Bursevî (ö. 1137/1725), Celvetiyye’nin ilk defa İbrâhim Zâhid-i Geylânî’den (ö. 690/1291) zuhur ettiğini söyler. Ancak Celvetiyye tarikat olarak Aziz Mahmud Hüdâyî zamanında teşekkül etmiştir. Bazı müellifler Celvetiyye’nin İbrâhim Zâhid-i Geylânî’nin devrinde “hilâl”, Üftâde (ö. 988/1580) zamanında “ay”, Hüdâyî döneminde “dolunay” durumunda bulunduğunu ifade ederler (Bursevî, Silsile-i Celvetiyye, s. 63).\n"
        "\n"
        "Esas itibariyle Halvetiyye’nin bir kolu olan Celvetiyye’nin silsilesi, İbrâhim Zâhid-i Geylânî’de aynı tarikatın kollarından Zâhidiyye, Safiyyüddîn-i Erdebîlî’de (ö. 735/1334) Safeviyye, Hacı Bayrâm-ı Velî’de (ö. 833/1429-30) Bayramiyye ile birleşmektedir. Tarikatın kurucusu Aziz Mahmud Hüdâyî’nin şeyhi Üftâde’nin Sünbül Sinan’a, kendisinin de Nûreddinzâde ve Kerîmüddin Halvetî gibi Halvetî ricâline mensup olmaları, Celvetiyye’nin Halvetiyye ile ilgisini ortaya koymaktadır. Nitekim Hüdâyî de, “Bizim tarîkimiz hem Halvetî hem Celvetî’dir” diyerek tarikatının Halvetiyye ile iç içe olduğuna işaret eder. Öte yandan Celvetiyye’nin Bayramiyye ile doğrudan ilgisi vardır. Celvetî şeyhlerinden Yâkub Afvî (ö. 1149/1736) Celvetiyye’nin Bayramiyye’den doğduğunu söyler (Hediyyetü’s-sâlikîn, s. 4). Aziz Mahmud Hüdâyî’nin tarikat silsilesi Üftâde, Hızır Dede (ö. 918/1512), Akbıyık Sultan (ö. 860/1456) vasıtasıyla Hacı Bayrâm-ı Velî’ye ulaştığından Celvetiyye Bayramiyye’nin bir şubesi sayılır. Öte yandan Bayramiyye silsilesinin Nakşibendiyye ile münasebeti dolayısıyla Celvetiyye bu tarikattan da bazı izler taşır. Meselâ Nakşibendiyye’deki “nazar berkadem”, “halvet der-encümen” ve “hafî zikir” Celvetiyye’de de vardır.\n"
        "\n"
        "Aziz Mahmud Hüdâyî’nin İstanbul’da büyük sayıya ulaşan müridlerinin yanı sıra çeşitli bölgelere gönderdiği halifeleri sayesinde Anadolu ve Balkanlar’da yayılmaya başlayan Celvetiyye özellikle İstanbul, İzmir, Balıkesir, Orta Anadolu ve Balkanlar’da bir hayli yaygınlaşmıştı. Hüdâyî’den sonra İstanbul’da aynı kuvvetle temsil edilmemekle birlikte nüfuzunu devam ettirmiş ve İstanbul son dönemlere kadar tarikatın en yaygın bulunduğu yer olma hüviyetini sürdürmüştür. Gerek Hüdâyî devrinde gerekse daha sonraki devirlerde Balkanlar’da Filibeli İsmâil Efendi, Saçlı İbrâhim Efendi, Atpazarî Osman Fazlı Efendi gibi seçkin şeyhler tarafından temsil edilen Celvetiyye Balkanlar’ın en yaygın tarikatlarından biri olmuş, ikinci merkezi durumunda bulunan Bursa’da ise Üftâde ve torunlarıyla, İsmâil Hakkı Bursevî gibi şeyhler vasıtasıyla son dönemlere kadar itibarını devam ettirmiştir.\n"
        "\n"
        "Celvetiyye, Aziz Mahmud Hüdâyî’nin vefatından sonra Selâmiyye (kurucusu Selâmi Ali Efendi [ö. 1104/1692]), Hakkıyye (kurucusu İsmâil Hakkı Bursevî), Fenâiyye (kurucusu Fenâî Ali Efendi [ö. 1158/1745]), Hâşimiyye (kurucusu Hâşim Baba [ö. 1197/1783]) adlı dört şubeye ayrılmıştır.\n"
        "\n"
        "Hz. Ali kanalıyla geldiği için cehrî zikri esas alan bir tarikat olan Celvetiyye’nin sülûk âdâbının temelini, Hüdâyî’nin “tevhid zikri” adını verdiği (Vâkıât Tercümesi, vr. 9a) kelime-i tevhid zikri teşkil eder. Sâlike intisabından itibaren tevhid zikri telkin edilir. Sâlik bu zikre kendi durumuna göre üç mertebede ve her birine ayrı ayrı niyet ederek devam eder. Mübtedî olan sâlik kelime-i tevhidi “lâ ma‘bûde illallah”ın (Allah’tan başka mâbud yoktur) mânasını düşünerek zikreder. Bu mertebe tevhidin ilk mertebesi olup bunun mânası şer‘î ve zâhirî mânadır. Mutavassıt olan sâlik ise kelime-i tevhidi “lâ matlûbe illallah” veya “lâ maksûde illallah” (Allah’tan başka maksadım yoktur) düşüncesiyle icra eder. Bu sırada kalpte bir Allah’ın dışında bir sevgi hissi duyulur ve o varlık peygamber veya velî sınıfından bir vasıta değilse o zaman “lâ mahbûbe illallah” (Allah’tan başka sevgili yoktur) diye düşünülerek zikredilir. Müntehî olan sâlik ise tevhidin “lâ mevcûde illallah” (Allah’tan başka varlık yoktur) mânasını düşünerek zikreder. Sâlik bu zikre, kâinatın itibarî varlığı nazarında zâil olup tevhidin nuru zâhir olana kadar devam eder. Hüdâyî tevhid zikrinin uygulama tarzını anlatırken (Ecvibe-i Mutasavvıfâne, vr. 5a) belli bir zaman tesbiti yapmakla beraber asıl amacın her an bu zikre devam etmek olduğunu söyler. Mübtedî sâlik tevhid zikrini cehrî, mertebesi yükseldikçe hafî olarak icra eder.\n"
        "\n"
        "Celvetiyye tarikatında tevhid zikri esas olmakla beraber Halvetî sülûkünün esası olan esmâ-i seb‘a (lâ ilâhe illallah, Allah, hû, hak, hay, kayyûm, kahhâr) zikrinin de büyük önemi vardır. Özellikle Hüdâyî’den sonraki dönemde Celvetî şeyhleri sâlike esmâ-i seb‘a zikrini telkin etmişlerdir.\n"
        "\n"
        "Tarikatın âdâbına göre Celvetiyye’ye intisap etmek isteyen mürid adayı istihare, istişare ve abdest gibi ön hazırlıkları yaptıktan sonra şeyhin huzuruna varıp elini dizine koyarak oturur ve şeyhi ile beraber üç defa, “Allah’tan amelî, fiilî ve kavlî bütün günahlarımın bağışlanmasını dilerim” (أستغفر الله من كل ذنب قولاً وفعلاً وعملاً) dedikten sonra yine istiğfar ederek “âmentü”yü okur. Bundan sonra şeyh tâlibe her gün 100 defa istiğfar etmesini, 100 salavat, 700 defa kelime-i tevhid okumasını, sabah namazından sonra tefekkürle meşgul olmasını, sonra da dört veya altı rek‘at işrak, kuşluk vaktinde iki, dört veya altı rek‘at duhâ (kuşluk), akşam namazından sonra altı rek‘at evvâbîn, gece de iki veya on iki rek‘at teheccüd namazı kılmasını, pazartesi, perşembe günleriyle zilhicce ve muharremin on gününde, receb ve şâbanın tamamında, şevvalin altı gününde oruç tutmasını, daima abdestli bulunmasını, abdest aldığı zaman iki rek‘at şükür namazı kılmasını söyler. Müride ayrıca sabah namazından sonra Hüdâyî’nin tertip ettiği ve “hizb-i Hüdâyî” diye meşhur olan virdin okunması telkin edilir.\n"
        "\n"
        "Celvetiyye’de sülûkün tabiat, nefis, ruh ve sır olmak üzere dört mertebesi vardır. Şeriatın mukabili olan ilk mertebede sâlik bedenî ihtiyaçlarını ibadetini engellemeyecek şekilde karşılar ve helâl olanlarla yetinirse nefis mertebesine yükselir. Bu mertebe, nefsi kötü huy ve fiillerden arındırma mertebesidir. Bu ise ancak sürekli mücahede ve riyâzetle gerçekleştirilebilir. Ruh ve sırrın ıslahı bu mücadele neticesinde mümkün olur. Bu mertebenin mukabili de tarikattır. Ruh mertebesi, sâlikin ruhu ile ilgi kurduğu ve mârifetullaha yöneldiği mertebedir. Bu mertebede ilm-i ledün esrarı da zâhir olmaya başladığından aynı zamanda keşf mertebesidir ve mârifet makamına tekabül eder. Mârifet ve ilâhî aşk makamına ulaşan sâlik son olarak sır mertebesine yükselir. Hakikatin mukabili olan bu mertebe mahv, fenâ, tecellî ve vuslat makamıdır. Sâlik bu mertebede kemale ermiş olarak mücâhedattan lezzet duymaya başlar (Vâkıât Tercümesi, vr. 13a-17b).\n"
        "\n"
        "Bu dört makamın her birini ayrı ayrı sembolik renklerle yorumlayan Hüdâyî’ye göre tabiat mertebesinin rengi siyahtır; siyah bedenin aslı olan toprağın sembolüdür. Nefis mertebesinin rengi olan kırmızı havanın sembolüdür. Ruh mertebesi sarı renk ile temsil edilir ve ateşe tekabül eder. Sır mertebesi ise saydam olup suyu temsil eder. Böylece dört makam ve mertebe “anâsır-ı erbaa” ile temsil edilmiş olur. Sâlik bu mertebeleri aşınca kendi vücudu ortadan kalkar, geriye vâcibü’l-vücûd olan Hakk’ın vücudu kalır. Celvetî dervişi, bu usul üzere sülûkünü tamamladıktan sonra şeyhi tarafından halife tayin edilerek kendisine irşad görevi verilir.\n"
        "\n"
        "Celvetî tacı on üç terkli olup kubbesi siyaha yakın koyu yeşildir; ortasında aynı renk bir düğme vardır. Celvetî Âsitânesi’ne mensup dervişlerin giydikleri tacın destarının ucu tuğ gibi ön taraftan gösterilir ve bu cemal alâmeti sayılır. Tacın on üç terkinden on ikisi kelime-i tevhidin harflerine, on iki imama ve esmâ-i seb‘adan mazhar olunan isme delâlet eder (Bursevî, Tamâmü’l-feyz, vr. 51a-b). Bir başka rivayete göre on üç terk on iki imam ile Hüdâyî’nin kutbiyetine işaret olup tacın tepesindeki düğme nübüvvet-i Muhammediyye’nin ifadesidir. Tacın ön kısmı mihrabî ve minberî, arka tarafı da kafesî biçimde sarılır ki bu şekil diğer tarikat taçlarının hiçbirinde yoktur. Celvetî Âsitânesi’ne devam eden muhiblere intisaplarından önce beyaz destarlı taç giydirilirdi. Tepesi siyah olmakla birlikte destarının sarılma şekli ilmiye sarığına benzediğinden bu tacı giyen muhiblere “Celvetî sofusu” denilmiştir. Tarikata intisap edip derviş olanlar yeşil destar sararlardı.\n"
        "\n"
        "Diğer tarikatlarda kıyam, devran, semâ gibi isimler verilen âyine Celvetiyye’de “nısf-ı kıyâm” adı verilir. Diz üstüne kalkılarak icra edilen bu âyine “Hızır kıyamı” da denir. Bu zikir tarzı ile ilgili iki rivayet vardır. Kuûd tevhidi esnasında Hüdâyî postunda otururken Hz. Peygamber’in ruhaniyetini müşahede etmiş, tâzim için ayağa kalkmak isteyince Hz. Peygamber işaret ederek ayağa kalkmamasını emretmiş, o da zikre dizi üzerinde devam etmiş, bu olaydan sonra Celvetiyye’de bu şekilde zikir yapmak gelenek halini almıştır. Bir başka rivayete göre Hüdâyî Hz. Peygamber’i değil Hızır’ı müşahede etmiştir. Bu sebeple nısf-ı kıyâma Hızır kıyamı da denilir. Nısf-ı kıyâm, Celvetiyye’nin merkezi Hüdâyî Dergâhı’nda cuma namazından sonra icra edilirdi. Zâkirbaşı kelime-i tevhid zikrini başlatır, toplu olarak ağır ağır on iki kelime-i tevhid çekildikten sonra zâkirbaşı “Yâ Allah hû” deyince diz üstü kalkılır. Bu sırada zâkirler Hüdâyî’nin ilâhilerinden birini okurlar. İlâhi bitip zâkirbaşı, “Yâ Allah hû” deyince kıyama kalkılırdı. Bir süre ism-i hû zikrine devam edildikten sonra zâkirbaşı ism-i Celâl (Allah) zikrine geçer, daha sonra üç defa “hû” der, zâkirler de uygun bir ilâhi okurlar, ilâhi bitmeden şeyh efendi yerini alır, ilâhinin sonunda okunan durak sessizce dinlenirdi. Daha sonra şeyh efendi, “Yâ Allah hû” deyince zikrin ikinci safhası başlamış olur. Giderek hızlanan “hû zikri” başlar, bir sağa, bir sola çevrilerek devam eder. Bu arada zâkirler usule göre ilâhi okurlar, yine bu sırada şeyh efendi ritmi değiştirerek üç ism-i Celâl okur. İlâhiler zikrin âhenk ve temposuna göre bir süre devam edip sona erdiğinde zâkirbaşı zâkirlerin birine işaret eder, o da bir başka ilâhiyi kendi başına okur, bitirince başkası devam ederdi. Şeyh efendinin gelişiyle birlikte başlayan zikrin bu bölümü yarım saat kadar devam ettikten sonra şeyh yüksek sesle söylediği uzun bir “hû” ile zikri keser. Zâkirler daha sonra ağır aksak usulünde cumhur ilâhisi okurlar, bu da bitince şeyh efendi kısa bir dua yapar ve böylece âyin tamamlanmış olur.\n"
        "\n"
        "Celvetiyye’nin Üsküdar’daki merkez dergâhında Hüdâyî’nin vefatından tekkelerin kapatılmasına kadar yirmi üç şeyh postnişin olmuştur . Dergâhın son şeyhi Abdülgafûr Âbid Efendi’dir (ö. 1946).\n"
        "\n"
        "Tarikatın merkezi olan İstanbul’da Celvetî meşihatı vaz‘olunduğu tesbit edilen otuz kadar tekkenin on altısı Üsküdar’dadır. Bu otuz tekkeden dokuzu (Hüdayî Âsitânesi, Selâmsız, Acıbadem, Kısıklı Selâmi Ali Efendi tekkeleriyle Fenâî Ali, İskender Baba, Bandırmalı, Şeyh Camii, Sarmaşık tekkeleri) kuruluşlarından son dönemlerine kadar tarikat değiştirmeden Celvetî olarak kalmış, bazıları birkaç defa (Küçükayasofya, Mehmed Paşa tekkeleri gibi), bir kısmı ise (Bezirgân Tekkesi) bir defa Celvetîler’in eline geçmiştir.\n"
        "\n"
        "Mutasavvıf ve şair hüviyetinin yanı sıra bir mûsikişinas olan tarikatın kurucusu Aziz Mahmud Hüdâyî yazdığı ilâhileri bizzat besteleyerek tekkesinde okutmuş, sonraki asırlarda yaşayan mûsikişinaslar onun manzumelerinden besteler yapmışlardır. Hüdâyî devrinde tekkede, aynı zamanda halifeleri olan Hâfız Kumral ve Şâban Dede gibi meşhur mûsikişinasların zâkirbaşılık yapmaları ve Celvetî şeyhlerinin birçoğunun bestekâr olması, bu tarikatta mûsıkiye verilen önemi gösterir. Âsitâne şeyhlerinden Divitçizâde Mehmed Efendi (ö. 1090/1679), Tâlib mahlasıyla yazdığı ilâhilerden bir kısmını bestelemişti. İstanbul’daki Celvetî meşâyihi ve mensuplarının yanı sıra Bursa Celvetîler’i de mûsikiyle yakından ilgilenmişlerdir. Meşhur Celvetî şeyhi İsmâil Hakkı Bursevî, Hüdâyî’nin bazı ilâhileriyle kendi yazdığı şiirleri çeşitli makamlarda bestelemiştir."</string>




</resources>
